<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
    <info>
        <name></name>
        <update version="1.0.1">
            <file name="spells.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Zenoverlordian/Aurora-Builder-The-Elements-Beyond/main/spells.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>
    
    <element name="Acid Cloud" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ACID_CLOUD">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a cloud of acidic vapor over the head of one creature you can see within range. The cloud follows the target as it moves and sprays acid upon it periodically. At the start of each of the target's turns while the cloud remains, the target and each other creature in the target's space must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 5d4 acid damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">The cloud lasts for the duration or until a wind of moderate or greater speed (at least 10 miles per hour) disperses it. Ifthe target ends any of its turns at least 50 feet away from where it began that turn, the spell immediately ends.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d4 for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Acid Ward" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ACID_WARD">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You are surrounded by a swirling shield of protective green acid that doesn't damage you or your equipment. You can end the spell early by using an action to dismiss it. Until the spell ends, you gain the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You have resistance to acid damage.</li>
                <li>You can't be restrained by nonmagical objects.</li>
                <li>Any creature that grapples you or begins its turn while grappling you takes 12d4 acid damage.</li>
                <li>Whenever a creature within 5 feet of you makes a melee attack against you, the creature has disadvantage on the attack, and it takes 8d4 acid damage before the attack hits or misses.</li>
                <li>When you are attacked with a weapon, the attack misses and the swirling acid consumes the weapon, dissolving it and destroying it. If ammunition was used, it is consumed instead This doesn't happen if the weapon is magical or a natural weapon, or if the attack used magical ammunition.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">A creature killed by this spell is dissolved into slime.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bit of solvent or a swamp frog</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Annihilation Disk" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ANNIHILATION_DISK">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You hurl a swirling disk of destructive force at one creature you can see within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 8d6 + 15 force damage and the spell ends. This spell ignores resistance, and targets with vulnerability to slashing damage have vulnerability to the spell's damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a miss, the disk flies past the target and begins flying through the air on its own, seeking out another target. Note the location ofyour target when you cast the spell At the start ofyour next turn, you must repeat the spell attack (no action) against the creature within range that is now closest to that space, possibly even attacking yourself. If this attack misses or has no target, repeat this process using the location of the last target when the spell attacked it, repeating the attack each round until the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">The disk uses blindsight to find its targets, not vision, and it weaves around obstacles to reach its target, so subsequent attacks after the first ignore half cover and three-quarters cover and do not suffer disadvantage if you cannot see the target. If multiple creatures are tied for being the closest to the disk when you repeat the attack, you choose which one the disk attacks.</p>
            <p class="indent">The disk damages objects in its path that aren't being worn or carried When this spell destroys an object or kills a creature, it is sliced in twain.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 2d6 for each slot level above 6th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Animate Tree" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ANIMATE_TREE">
        <supports>Druid</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a Large or Huge non-creature plant and fill it with animating magic. Until the spell ends, the target is a creature and uses a treant's statistics, except that it can't speak, it lacks the Animate Trees ability, and it has Intelligence and Charisma scores of 1. The spell ends when the treant drops to 0 hit points. (The DM has game statistics for this creature).</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell is cast, the target uproots, gains the ability to move its limbs, roots, vines, and so forth, grows to size Huge if it was smaller, and gains senses similar to a human's. It is friendly to you and your companions for the duration. Roll initiative for the treant, which has its own turns. It obeys any verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don't issue any commands to the treant, it defends itself from hostile creatures but otherwise takes no actions.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the target stops being a creature and becomes inanimate once again, returning to its original size in the process. The plant then takes root in its current location if possible.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">the bark of a tree that fell on its own</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Barrier" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BARRIER">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You shroud one creature that you can see within range in a protective bubble of rubbery force that has hit points equal to 2d8 + your spellcasting ability modifier and lasts for the duration. If the target would take damage before the spell ends, the ward blocks that damage and takes the damage instead The ward cannot block psychic or poison damage unless it is dealt by an attack. If the ward is reduced to 0 hit points, the target takes any remaining damage and the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the ward hit points increase by 2d8 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Beluud's Bile Blossom" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BELUUDS_BILE_BLOSSOM">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You blast one creature or object that you can see within range with a spiraling beam of greenish-yellow acidic bile that crashes over the target, bursting and spraying beyond it. You make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 12d4 acid damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, hit or miss, the blast sprays around the target, creating a 60-foot cone of acidic spray originating from the space just in front of the target. The cone is facing away from you and must include the target in its area. Each creature in the area (including the target) must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 12d4 acid damage, or half as much damage on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the acid damage dealt (for both parts) increases by 2d4 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">two animal stomachs, one inside the other</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Beluud's Boiling Bubble" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BELUUDS_BOILING_BUBBLE">
        <supports>Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a steaming bubble of boiling water to capture one creature that you can see within range. The target must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, it is trapped inside the bubble and it takes 4d8 fire damage. On a success, it takes half as much damage and the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">While trapped by the bubble, the target is restrained and unable to breathe unless it can breathe water, and at the start ofeach of its turns, it must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become blinded until the start of its next tum. Also, when the target ends its turn within the bubble, it takes 4d8 fire damage, and the bubble rises 10 feet higher into the air. The target does not fall while it is trapped in the bubble.</p>
            <p class="indent">To escape the bubble, the target can use its action to make a Strength or Dexterity check (its choice) against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself from the bubble and falls unless it can fly or stop the fail and the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the bubble vanishes, and each creature trapped inside falls unless it can stop the fall</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a boiled frog</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Beluud's Brutal Jaunt" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BELUUDS_BRUTAL_JAUNT">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You leap through space in a blur, smashing into a foe as you pass between realms. You teleport to an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see within range. You can also choose up to one creature in a line 5 feet wide originating at the space you left and ending at the space you teleported to. The target must make a Constitution saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a failed saving throw, the target takes 3d10 force damage and is knocked prone. On a successful saving throw, the target takes half as much damage and is not knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the maximum number of creatures you can target increases by one for each slot level above 2nd</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a spiked ring</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Beluud's Corrosive Caress" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BELUUDS_CORROSIVE_CARESS">
        <supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You attempt to touch a creature as you conjure magical acid into the palm of your hand. Make a melee spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 5d4 acid damage, and nonmagical armor worn by the target is partly dissolved and takes a permanent and cumulative -2 penalty to the AC it offers. The armor is destroyed if the penalty reduces its AC to 10.</p>
            <p class="indent">Armor that is affected or destroyed by this spell can be fully restored with the mending spelL or through the use of appropriate tools.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 2d4 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Blades of Grass" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BLADES_OF_GRASS">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Up to 15 pieces of grass or conifer leaves that you touch transform into magical weaponry. You transform each object into your choice of an arrow, blowgun needle, or crossbow bolt. Ifyou target no more than two objects, your choices for transformation also include a dagger, shortsword, scimitar, rapier, longsword, or greatsword.</p>
            <p class="indent">The weapons and ammunition are constructed out of plant material and weigh half as much as normal They are extra sharp, granting them a +1 bonus to damage rolls. You can choose to have them be magical; if you don't, the spell does not use concentration.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ammunition created by this spell is destroyed when it hits a target. When the spell ends, all the weaponry turns to dust.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">pieces of grass or conifer leaves</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Blazing Thunderbolt Strike" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BLAZING_THUNDERBOLT_STRIKE">
        <supports>Paladin, Ranger, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>The next time you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack during this spell's duration, a bolt of flaming lightning streaks down from above and strikes the target at the same moment. The attack deals an extra 2d8 lightning damage and 3d6 fire damage to the target, and the target must make a Constitution saving throw. It has disadvantage on the saving throw if it is wearing armor made of metal</p>
            <p class="indent">On a failed saving throw, the target is knocked prone, can't take reactions until the start ofyour next turn, and is lit ablaze. Until a creature takes an action to douse the fire, it takes 1d10 fire damage at the start of each of its turns. This fire continues even after the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">If you are outdoors in stormy conditions when you hit with the attack, the lightning damage increases by 1d8. If the target is already ablaze when you hit with the attack, the fire damage increases by 2d6.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the lightning damage dealt increases by 1d8 (or 2d8 in stormy conditions) and the fire damage dealt increases by 1d6 (or 2d6 if the target is already ablaze) for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">component</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Boulder Shot" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BOULDER_SHOT">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You summon a boulder from an unoccupied space adjacent to a surface within range that you can see, like a floor, walL or ceiling. The surface doesn't have to be made of a single contiguous materiaL but it must mostly be made of earth, sand, stone, metaL crystaL or another suitable earthen or stone-like materiaL and it must be at least 1 foot deep, or else the spell fails.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the boulder appears, you use magic to hurl it at one creature or object within 120 feet of the boulder that you can see. Make a spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 6d10 nonmagical bludgeoning damage and must make a Strength saving throw, falling prone and being pushed 15 feet on a failed save. On a miss, the target takes half damage and is not knocked prone or pushed.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell attack you make with this spell determines cover and line of effect (including the direction to push) as if it was made from the location where the boulder was summoned rather than your location, and it ignores disadvantage caused by a target being prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell deals double damage to objects and structures.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Burrow" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_BURROW">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You become magically attuned to the earth and ground around you, enabling you to traverse it like a fish does water. Until the spell ends, you have tremorsense that extends out to 60 feet around you, you gain a burrowing speed of 40 feet, and you can hold your breath for 10 times as long as normal.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifthis spell ends while you are underground and you lack a burrowing speed, you are trapped underground Until you are excavated or you manage some way out on your own, you are buried (See Appendix A, page 225).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a groundworm or mole's claw</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Caldera" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CALDERA">
        <supports>Druid, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>There are two possible uses for the spelL granting either immediate or long-term effects.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Lava.</em></strong> If you cast this spell using 1 action, the ground within 60 feet of a point that you choose within range is transformed into superheated molten lava that extends 5 feet deep until the spell ends. The lava sheds bright light for 30 feet and dim light for an additional 30 feet beyond that.A creature walking on the lava must spend 4 feet of movement for every 1 foot it moves. Each creature that touches the lava for the first time on a turn must make a Dexterity saving throw, unless it is already restrained by the lava. On a failed save, it takes 8d8 fire damage and is restrained by the lava. On a success, it takes half damage and it isn't restrained</p>
            <p class="indent">Each creature that starts its turn within 15 feet of the lava or enters that area for the first time on a turn takes 4d8 fire damage, or 12d8 fire damage if it is restrained by the lava. When a restrained creature ends its turn, it sinks into the lava. In addition, whenever a creature falls prone within the lava or ends its turn while prone within the lava, it takes 8d8 additional fire damage and sinks into the lava. This spell treats creatures that cannot be prone as if they are always prone instead</p>
            <p class="indent">A restrained creature can use an action to attempt to escape. It makes a Strength check against your spell save DC, with disadvantage if it has sunk into the lava. On a success, it frees itself and stands atop the lava.</p>
            <p class="indent">The lava damages objects in the area and ignites flammable objects that aren't being worn or carried, and it flows downhill and through holes or channels (at the DM's discretion} When the spell ends, the lava cools and hardens into black obsidian glass. The obsidian is broken wherever a creature would be trapped inside.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Magma.</em></strong> If you cast this spell over 1 hour, you call forth magma deep beneath the land The spell's material com- ponents are consumed, the ground level rises by twenty feet, and if there is a volcano at your location, it grows taller and stronger. Doing this at the same location once every 30 days for 10 years creates a permanent volcano, topped with a permanent caldera that functions the same as the Lava version of this spell The volcano has a radius of at least 1 mile at its base. It's activity leveL topography, and growth rate are determined by the DM.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action or 1 hour</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute, or Instantaneous if cast over 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a diamond worth at least 800 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Cannon Blast" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CANNON_BLAST">
        <supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You release a blast of flame behind you that rockets you into the air. You fly up to 60 feet in a straight line and stop at the first creature you contact. You can choose to make a melee spell attack against the creature, hitting it with a magic barrier. On a hit, the target takes 3d6 fire damage and 2d6 force damage, and it must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be knocked prone. On a miss, the target takes half as much damage and isn't knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">For this tum, your barrier grants you resistance to damage from falls, and falls do not knock you prone upon landing. Upon finishing the movement and attack caused by this speli you fall if you are still aloft, unless you can stop the fall.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the force damage dealt increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 2nd</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (60 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">1 turn</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Cold Snap" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_COLD_SNAP">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>With a snap of your fingers you banish heat from a target. There are two possible uses for the spell: targeting either one creature that you can see within range or targeting an area of liquid, such as water, acid, mud, snow, quicksand, or lava.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifyou target a creature, it must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, the target takes 5d10 cold damage and until the end ofyour next tum, its speed is reduced to 0 feet and it has disadvantage on weapon attack rolls. It also gains one level of exhaustion unless it has resistance or immunity to the spell's damage. On a success, it only takes half damage and it doesn't suffer any other effects.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifyou target an area, your magic affects a portion of liquid that you can see within range and fits into a 30 foot cube. The affected liquid is frozen solid for 10 minutes, provided that there are no creatures in the area. Not all liquids lose their properties when frozen. For example, frozen lava may still be extremely hot to the touch, and frozen acid may still sting or even cause damage in extreme concentrations.</p>
            <p class="indent">Any levels of exhaustion caused by this spell are removed from a creature when it finishes a short or long rest in a warm environment.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1dl10 for each slot level above 3rd</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round or 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Combustion" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_COMBUSTION">
        <supports>Druid, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You become a locus for the primal force of combustion itself. Until the spell ends, the following effects occur within 90 feet ofyou and are not blocked by total cover:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Objects in the area have vulnerability to fire damage.</li>
                <li>Flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried are automatically on fire.</li>
                <li>Fire in the area cannot be doused, extinguished, or smothered and doesn't require air.</li>
                <li>Each creature that enters the area or starts its tum in it is lit ablaze. A burning creature takes 1d10 fire damage at the start of each of its turns until someone takes an action to douse the fire.</li>
                <li>Metal objects in the area are heated A creature in physical contact with a heated object takes 2d8 fire damage at the end of each ofyour turns, and it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks while holding or wearing a heated object unless it is immune to fire damage.</li>
                <li>When another effect in the area rolls a 1 or a 2 on a damage die for fire damage, the die is rerolled and must use the new roli even if the new roll is a 1 or 2.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">When you cast the speli you can choose any number of creatures and objects to be completely unaffected by the spell</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (90 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Conflagration" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CONFLAGRATION">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Fire springs from the ground within 10 feet of a point that you can see within range and lasts until the spell ends or until it is extinguished by any means. The fire extends 5 feet above the ground Each time a creature starts its tum in the fire or enters it for the first time on a tum, it must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or else take 1d10 fire damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell ignites any flammable objects in the fire that aren't being worn or carried.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the radius of the effect increases by 10 feet for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">flint and tinder, or a flame</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Conjure Arms" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CONJURE_ARMS">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Until the end ofyour turn, when you would be able to draw a weapon or shield, you can instead conjure an object of that form into your hand(s) as if you'd drawn it. You cannot create items ofvalue greater than 50 gp in total Ifyou conjure a shield, you can choose to have it appear already equipped to you.</p>
            <p class="indent">Equipment made by this spell is slightly translucent and obviously conjured, and is no sturdier than equipment oflow quality, but otherwise functions the same as any nonmagical version for the duration. Though they are conjured by magic, they are not magical If the spell ends, you cast the spell again, or you do not hold the equipment for an entire round, the conjured equipment instantly vanishes.</p>
            <p class="indent">When you reach 5th leveL this spell's duration increases to 10 minutes. It increases to 1 hour at 11th leveL and it increases to 8 hours at 17th level.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, taken at the start of your turn</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Conjure Critters" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CONJURE_CRITTERS">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You summon minor fey spirits that take the form of beasts and appear in unoccupied spaces that you can see within range. Choose one of the following options for what appears:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>One beast of challenge rating 1/4 or lower</li>
                <li>Two beasts of challenge rating 1/8 or lower</li>
                <li>Four beasts of challenge rating 0</li>
                <li>Eight beasts of challenge rating 0, but these beasts can't deal any damage, regardless of their statistics.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">Each beast is also considered fey, and it disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">The summoned creatures are friendly to you and your companions. You roll initiative for the summoned creatures as a group, which has its own turns. They obey any verbal commands that you issue to them (no action required by you} Ifyou don't issue any commands to them, they defend themselves from hostile creatures, but otherwise take no actions.</p>
            <p class="indent">The DM has the creatures' statistics.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using certain higher-level spell slots, you choose one of the summoning options above, and more creatures appear: twice as many with a 3rd-level slot, three times as many with a 5th-level slot, four times as many with a 7th-level slot, and five times as many with a 9th-level slot.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Corrosive Plume" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CORROSIVE_PLUME">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A wave of acidic gas erupts from your hands in a line 100 feet long and 15 feet wide. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failure, a creature takes 13d6 acid damage, and if it is wearing nonmagical armor that isn't adamantine, that armor is dissolved and destroyed On a success, a creature takes halfas much damage and nothing else.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell damages objects in the area.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">100 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Cyclone" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CYCLONE">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A swirling coil offierce wind rises around one creature that you can see within range. The target must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failure, the target takes 5d8 bludgeoning damage, you can choose to push it up to 15 feet in any direction, and if the target is Huge or smaller, it is thrown 30 feet up into the air. It remains aloft until the end ofyour next turn, at which point it falls unless it can stop the fall While held aloft by this spell a creature is restrained if it cannot fly.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a successful saving throw, the target takes half damage and isn't pushed or launched into the air.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Cyclone Strike" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_CYCLONE_STRIKE">
        <supports>Ranger, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Slicing wind swirls around you in a cyclone as you make a magical spinning strike. You make a melee attack with a weapon that you are holding against each creature of your choice within the spell's range. Ifyou are holding two weapons that you can use for two-weapon fighting, you can make an attack with each ofthose weapons against each target, using two-weapon fighting rules to determine each attack's damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">For these attacks, the weapons count as magical for the purposes of overcoming resistance and their reach is the spell's range. After the attacks, the wind disperses gas or vapor and extinguishes unprotected flames that are torch-sized or smaller within 20 feet of you.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the start ofyour next turn, any ranged weapon attacks made against you have disadvantage.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">10 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">one or two weapons</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Dark Lagoon" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_DARK_LAGOON">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a 60 foot cube of sloshing murky water centered on a point that you can see within range. The water does not leave the confines of the cubic area, nor is it affected by gravity. The water is heavily obscured for everyone except you. To you, it only appears lightly obscured You can breathe and speak in this conjured water, and you have a swim speed equal to your walking speed while you are within it.</p>
            <p class="indent">The cube ofwater appears instantly, and creatures whose space is inside the edge of the area can make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, they are trapped inside the area. On a successful saving throw, a creature can use its reaction to move up to its speed to an unoccupied space that is outside the area. Once the spell has been cast, the water tension on each side of the cube makes it tough to escape. Any creature that attempts to move out of the area must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed saving throw, it is unable to leave the area this turn.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, you choose to have the water either vanish or remain. If it remains, the water loses its magic, and collapses in a wave. Each creature in a 40-foot radius on the ground under the cube must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 6d6 nonmagical bludgeoning damage, is pushed 20 feet away from the center of the effect, and is knocked prone. This wave ofwater also pushes and damages objects that aren't being held or carried</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a conch shell</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Deep Freeze" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_DEEP_FREEZE">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You freeze the liquid inside one creature that you can see within range. The target is paralyzed until the spell ends, and it must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 7d10 + 30 cold damage, or half as much damage on a success. Water elementals make this saving throw with disadvantage and are never immune to this paralysis. The target makes another Constitution saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the spell on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on creatures that are immune to cold damage, constructs, or undead A creature killed by this spell is transformed completely into ice.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Dive" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_DIVE">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch one creature and imbue it with aquatic magic, allowing it to traverse watery environments with ease. Until the spell ends, the target gains a swimming speed of 60 feet, it can breathe water, and it doesn't suffer disadvantage on attack rolls for being underwater.</p>
            <p class="indent">While the spell lasts, the target also has advantage on saving throws made to resist the dark lagoon, scalding sphere, and watery sphere spells, and it ignores any difficult terrain or obscurement caused by the presence of water (but not the effects of water currents).</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot above 2nd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">fish scales and a sea shell</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Drown" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_DROWN">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a globe of magical water to surround a foe's head and drown it. Choose one creature in range that you can see. The target must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed saving throw, the target cannot speak and has disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight or hearing until the spell ends. While the spell continues, it takes 2d8 bludgeoning damage at the start of each of its turns.</p>
            <p class="indent">At the end ofeach of its turns, the creature can repeat the saving throw. On a success, the creature breaks free and the spell ends. Creatures that can breathe water or do not have to breathe automatically succeed on the saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 2nd When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the duration increases to Concentration up to 10 minutes, and the target can only hold its breath for up to 30 seconds before suffocating.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">teeth, seaweed, and seawater</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Earth Stomp" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_EARTH_STOMP">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You stomp the ground, causing it to shake and flinging bits of earth and stone at nearby foes. Each creature within range other than you must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 1d6 bludgeoning damage. The spell fails if the caster is not touching the ground when it is cast.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">5 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Earth Whelm" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_EARTH_WHELM">
        <supports>Druid, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You use primal magic to confuse the elements in a 150-foot cube centered on a point that you can see within range. Ground in the area becomes fluid without losing its shape. This effect extends through total cover, below the ground's surface. Each creature and object on the ground in the area sinks partially into the ground, as if the ground were a liquid.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ground in the area must be traversed as if it were a water-like liquid - walking or burrowing normally is impossible. The ground is heavily obscured and difficult terrain. A creature that is entirely submerged in it must hold its breath or suffocate, and any creature that ends its turn while touching it must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature is pulled 20 feet downward, below the ground's surface.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each structure touching the ground in the area sinks 5 feet into the ground at the start of each ofyour turns for the duration. The ground flows around corners and into open structures, affecting the creatures inside, but it can't flow through total cover.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, either because your concentration is broken or because you decide to end it, ground in the area returns to its normal state. Each creature that is entirely immersed in ground becomes trapped Until it is excavated or it manages some way out on its own, it is buried (See Appendix A, page 225).</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell only affects ground composed primarily of some form of earth, such as dirt, sand, clay, crystaL ash, metaL etc. It does not affect other materials like bone, wood, ice, etc.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">1 mile</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a vial of quicksand</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Electric Interdiction" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ELECTRIC_INTERDICTION">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Just before the event can occur, you blast the triggering creature with lightning, forcing it to make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, the target takes 10d8 lightning damage and must make a Constitution saving throw. On a successful Dexterity saving throw, the target takes half damage and no other effects.</p>
            <p class="indent">If the target fails the Constitution saving throw, the action or effect that triggered this spell is foiled. Any spell slots or abilities that the target would have expended are still expended Its speed is reduced to 0 feet for the rest of the turn, and if it is the target's turn, the turn ends immediately.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 9th leveL the damage dealt increases by 2d8.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, taken when a creature within range moves, uses an action, bonus action, reaction, or legendary action, or interacts with an object</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Elemental Chains" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ELEMENTAL_CHAINS">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure magical chains of elemental energy that lurch toward your foes to shackle them. Choose up to five creatures that you can see within range, and choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each target must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a target is restrained until the spell ends. At the end ofeach ofyour turns while the spell lasts, you can choose to pull any number of targets restrained by this spell up to 20 feet closer to you.</p>
            <p class="indent">A creature restrained by the chains takes 6d8 damage of the chosen type at the start of each of its turns. In addition, it can use its action to make a Strength or Dexterity check (its choice) against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, you can target up to one additional creature for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a length of chains, at least 10 ft.</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Elemental Meteor" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ELEMENTAL_METEOR">
        <supports>Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You beckon an elemental meteor to descend from above and strike the ground in a fiery explosion at a point you can see within range. Each creature within a 30-foot sphere centered on that point must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 3d10 fire damage and 3d10 bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent">After impact, the flaming meteor lurches out of its crater, awakens, and separates into a fire elemental and an earth elementaL each ofwhich disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends. Each of the elementals takes bludgeoning damage equal to half its maximum hit points from the impact. Creatures in the earth elemental's space are pushed away from the center of the impact point until they are completely outside the elemental's space.</p>
            <p class="indent">The elementals are friendly to you and your companions for the duration. Roll initiative for the elementals, which have their own turns. They obey any verbal commands that you issue to them (no action required by you). If you don't issue any commands to the elementals,they defend themselves from hostile creatures but otherwise take no actions .</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifyour concentration is broken, the elementals don't disappear. Instead, you lose control of the elementals, they become hostile toward you and your companions, and they might attack. An uncontrolled elemental can't be dismissed by you, and it disappears 1 hour after you summoned it.</p>
            <p class="indent">The DM has the elementals' statistics. This spell deals double damage to objects and structures in the area of the meteor impact. Additionally, ground within the area becomes difficult terrain until cleared Each 5-foot-diameter portion of the area requires at least 1 minute to clear by hand.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">500 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a piece of a meteor</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Elemental Step" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ELEMENTAL_STEP">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You transform into a bolt of lightning and race instantly across the landscape, teleporting yourself to a location of your choice within range. The destination you choose must be known to you, and it must be on the same plane of existence as you.</p>
            <p class="indent">When you arrive at your destination, you return to normal and a column of lightning crashes down around you in a 20-foot-radius, 200-foot-high cylinder centered on you. Flame blasts from you as well filling a 40-foot radius sphere centered on you which spreads around corners. Each other creature in either area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failure, a creature takes 8d8 lightning damage if it's in the column and 10d6 fire damage if it's in the sphere, or half as much damage on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent">Your arrival also creates a wave of seismic tremors in a 60-foot cube centered on a point ofyour choice. The cube extends through total cover and must contain your new space. It also creates a tide of freezing ice and mist in a 60-foot cone emanating from you. Other creatures in either area must each make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 4d12 bludgeoning damage and is knocked prone if it's in the cube, and it takes 5d10 cold damage and has its speed reduced by 30 feet until the end of its next turn if it's in the cone. On a success, a creature takes half as much damage and isn't knocked prone or slowed.</p>
            <p class="indent">Any ground in the cube is smashed and broken by the tremors. It becomes difficult terrain until cleared, with each 5-foot-square portion of terrain requiring at least 1 minute to clear by hand.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell damages objects, and it ignites flammable objects in the sphere or cylinder that aren't being worn or carried.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">10 miles</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Encasing Ice" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ENCASING_ICE">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a block of ice at a location within range. The ice consists of up to three 15-foot-cubes, which you can arrange as you wish. Each cube must have at least one face adjacent to the face ofanother cube. The ice is a magical object with 20d6 + 100 hit points and 16 AC. It grants cover and occupies space. It has immunity to cold damage, vulnerability to bludgeoning, fire, and thunder damage, and resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage dealt by nonmagical weapons. The ice lasts until it reaches 0 hit points or the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each creature in the ice when it appears can make a Dexterity saving throw. On a success, it uses its reaction to move up to half its speed so that it is no longer within the block of ice. Otherwise, it is trapped in the ice.</p>
            <p class="indent">The ice is translucent, so things can be seen through it, and the inside is lightly obscured When you cast the spell, you choose whether the ice is hollow or not.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Hollow.</em></strong> Each creature trapped in the ice block is pushed entirely inside the ice if it wasn't already. The inside is cool and lightly obscured by mist, and the walls of the ice are 1 foot thick.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Not Hollow.</em></strong> Each creature trapped in the ice block is restrained until the spell ends or it escapes.A trapped creature must make a Constitution saving throw at the start ofeach of its turns, taking 6d10 cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success. Any creature whose space is entirely within the ice is also paralyzed and can't breathe while restrained by it.</p>
            <p class="indent">A creature restrained by the ice can use its action to attempt to escape by breaking free of the ice, even if it is paralyzed by the ice. It makes a Strength check against your spell save DC, with disadvantage if it's paralyzed by the ice. On a success, it frees itself and breaks the ice in its space. When the ice surrounding a creature is broken in this way, it is freed even if it didn't attempt to escape. Every 5-foot cube portion of ice that is broken reduces the block's hit points by 15.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bit of water</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Enhance Body" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ENHANCE_BODY">
        <supports>Artificer, Cleric, Paladin, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch one creature, imbuing the target with magic that enhances and empowers its body. Choose either Strength or Dexterity to empower. Until the spell ends, the target gains the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>The target has advantage on ability checks that use the chosen ability score and on saving throws made to maintain concentration.</li>
                <li>The target's speed increases by 10 feet.</li>
                <li>The target has advantage on weapon attacks.</li>
                <li>When the target takes the Attack action, it gains a bonus to the damage rolls ofeach weapon attack it makes as part of that action. The bonus is equal to your spellcasting modifier (minimum +1).</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Envenomed Weapon" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ENVENOMED_WEAPON">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a weapon and wreathe it in magical venom. Until the spell ends, the weapon is magical if it wasn't already, and each time an attack using the weapon hits a creature, it must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 3d6 extra poison damage from the attack.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a vial of poison</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Explosive Rift" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_EXPLOSIVE_RIFT">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You clap your hands together, sending out a wave of explosive gas and flames that blast outward in a wall emanating out from you in a direction you choose. The wall lasts until the spell ends. It is 5 feet wide, 30 feet talL and up to 90 feet long, but you can choose a shorter length. The wall's space is lightly obscured and difficult terrain. Any ranged weapon attacks that pass in or out of the wall's area have disadvantage.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each creature within 5 feet of the wall when it appears must make a Strength saving throw. A creature must also make this saving throw when it starts its turn in the wall or enters the wall for the first time on a turn. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 8d10 fire damage and is pushed 20 feet away from the wall and knocked prone. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes halfdamage and isn't pushed or knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell ignites flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried, and the ground in the area is smashed by the spell's initial blast. Ifany ground in the area is loose earth or stone, it becomes difficult terrain until cleared, with each 5-foot-square portion requiring at least 1 minute to clear by hand</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the fire damage dealt increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (90 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Fingers of Lightning" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FINGERS_OF_LIGHTNING">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your hands arc with electricity as you create 4 lines, each 100 feet long and 5 feet wide, emanating from you in directions ofyour choice. Each line has its own direction and lines can overlap, but they must all fit within a 180 degree angle from you.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each creature within the spell's area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 7d6 lightning damage plus 1d6 lightning damage for each line area that they are within. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">The lightning ignites flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, you create an additional line of lightning for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (100-foot line)</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bit of fur; a piece of amber, a glass or crystal rod; and four copper pins</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Fist of Flame" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FIST_OF_FLAME">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You launch a blast of flame and kinetic force at one target you can see within range. Make a ranged spell attack against it. On a hit, the target takes 4d8 + 20 fire damage and 4d8 + 20 bludgeoning damage. It must also succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become stunned until the start ofyour next turn, and if you choose so, it must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 50 feet away from you and knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a miss, the target takes half damage and it isn't stunned, pushed, or knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifthe target is an object, it automatically fails any saving throws for this spell This spell ignites flammable objects that aren't being worn or carried.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 9th leveL the fire and bludgeoning damage dealt both increase by 2d8.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Flaring Weapon" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FLARING_WEAPON">
        <supports>Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a weapon and cause it to erupt with blazing hot fire when it is drawn. For the duration, the weapon emits bright light for 20 feet and dim light for another 20 feet while it is being held, it is magical if it was not already, and attacks made with the weapon deal bonus fire damage on a hit equal to 3d8 + your Spellcasting modifier.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the weapon is used to score a critical hit or hit with an opportunity attack, if the attack's target is flammable or is a creature, it is lit ablaze. It instantly takes 1d10 fire damage, and until a creature takes an action to douse the fire, it takes 1d10 fire damage again at the start of each of its turns.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Flash" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FLASH">
        <supports>Cleric, Paladin, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You burst with blinding light that shines briefly from your skin before fading away. Each other creature within range must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature is blinded until the end of your next turn, and any opportunity attacks it makes against you this turn automatically miss.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the end ofyour next turn, you shed bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">5 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bit of phosphorus</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Force of Nature" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FORCE_OF_NATURE">
        <supports>Druid</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure fey spirits to temporarily inhabit up to three Small or larger non-creature plants you can see within range. Until the spell ends, each target is a creature and uses the statistics for an awakened tree (CR 21 except that it can't speak, it has Intelligence and Charisma scores of 1, and it is considered a fey as well as a plant. (The DM has game statistics for these creatures.)</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell is cast, each target uproots, grows to size Large if smaller, gains the ability to move its limbs, roots, vines, creepers, and so forth, and gains senses similar to a human's. The plants are friendly to you and your companions. Roll initiative for the plants as a group, which has its own turns. They obey any verbal commands that you issue to them (no action required by you). Ifyou don't issue any commands to them, they defend themselves from hostile creatures, but otherwise take no actions.</p>
            <p class="indent">When a target is reduced to 0 hit points or when the spell ends, it stops being a creature and becomes inanimate once again, returning to its original size in the process. The plant then takes root in its current location if possible.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the number of plants you can target increases by one.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a staff made from a sapling</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Force Strike" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FORCE_STRIKE">
        <supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>As part of the action used to cast this spelL you must make a melee attack with a weapon against one target within the spell's range, otherwise the spell fails. Your reach for this melee attack is the range of the spell instead of its normal reach and the attack also counts as a ranged spell attack.</p>
            <p class="indent">Your weapon projects a wave of magical force in the shape of the blow toward your target. On a hit, the target suffers the attack's normal effects, except the weapon deals force damage for this attack instead of its normal damage type.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell's damage increases when you reach higher levels. At 5th leveL the attack deals an extra 1d8 force damage. At 11th level this increases to 2d8 bonus damage, and at 17th level the bonus increases to 3d8.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a melee weapon</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Frost Armor" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_FROST_ARMOR">
        <supports>Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You point at one creature that you can see within range that is wearing armor. The target's armor becomes frosted and icy until the spell ends, protecting the target and granting it the following benefits while worn:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>The target has resistance to cold damage.</li>
                <li>The target has a +2 bonus to AC.</li>
                <li>When the target is hit with a melee attack by an attacker within 5 feet of it, if the attacker doesn't have resistance or immunity to cold damage, its speed is reduced by 15 feet and it has disadvantage on weapon attack rolls until the end of its next turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a small crystal and a metal armlet</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Gale Weapons" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GALE_WEAPONS">
        <supports>Ranger, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>One or two weapons that you are holding are enveloped in small whirlwinds. For the duration, the weapons are magical if they weren't already, and they also have a +1 bonus to damage rolls. This effect is suppressed for a weapon while you aren't holding it.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, if you use an affected weapon to make a weapon attack on your turn, the attack gains benefits based on whether it is melee or ranged.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Melee.</em></strong> The attack's reach is tripled, but it counts as both a melee weapon attack and a ranged spell attack if it is made outside the weapon's normal reach.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Ranged.</em></strong> The attack ignores disadvantage caused by long-range, being underwater, or the effects of wind, and the weapon returns to one ofyour free hands at the end ofyour turn if it has the thrown property.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Gate Walk" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GATE_WALK">
        <supports>Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure spinning rings of magical light around the ankles and wrists ofone creature you can see within range that last for the duration. Using these bands, the target can conjure small and fleeting spatial gateways to aid in combat. Until the spell ends, the target gains the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>As a bonus action on its turn and as a reaction when the spell is cast, the target can teleport up to 15 feet to an unoccupied space that it can see.</li>
                <li>Whenever the target makes an attack on its turn, it can open a small arcane gateway for the attack to pass through. If it is a melee attack, the target can increase the reach of that attack up to 60 feet. If it is a ranged attack, it ignores half cover, three-quarters cover, and long distance penalties.</li>
                <li>Whenever the target hits a creature with a weapon attack, the weapon is treated as magical for the purpose ofovercoming resistances with that attack, and the attack deals 2d8 bonus force damage. This bonus damage can only be dealt once per turn.</li>
                <li>When the target is hit by an attack, it can use its reaction to open a small arcane gateway to disrupt the attack. The attacker must reroll the attack roll and use the new result.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a glass bangle</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Glide" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GLIDE">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You weave magic in a swirl as you falL creating an invisible sheet of force much like a glider or parachute in one or two ofyour hands that allows you to slow your descent and convert it to horizontal movement.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the spell ends, you fall no faster than 100 feet per round and you do not take falling damage. While you are holding the glider with two hands, you can move up to 2 feet horizontally for every 1 foot you descend while falling.</p>
            <p class="indent">Your aerial movement using this spell is highly affected by air currents. You can be blown off-course if the wind around you is significantly unfavorable. Ifyou are no longer holding the glider at any time, the spell ends. When the spell ends, you fall if you are still aloft, unless you can stop the fall.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd leveL the maximum duration increases to 10 minutes. A slot of 3rd level or higher increases it to 1 hour.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when you fall</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Glistening Acid Slick" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GLISTENING_ACID_SLICK">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a spray of translucent acid that covers the ground in a 60-foot cone. Until the spell ends, ground in the area is covered by slippery patches of foaming acid, making it difficult terrain. When the area appears, each creature in the area takes 2d4 acid damage and must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone. A creature that enters the area or ends its turn there takes 2d4 acid damage and must also succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, whenever a creature falls prone within the area or ends its turn while prone within the area, it takes 6d4 acid damage. This spell treats creatures that cannot be prone as if they are always prone instead.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell only affects creatures that are on the ground.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (60 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Globe of Winter" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GLOBE_OF_WINTER">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A miniature blizzard briefly rages in a 30-foot radius sphere centered on you, pelting the area with ice and cold The blizzard spreads around corners. Each other creature in the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 11d8 cold damage, is restrained until the end of its next turn and has its speed reduced to Ofeet. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes half damage and only has its speed reduced by 20 feet.</p>
            <p class="indent">A creature with reduced speed because of this spell recovers up to 10 feet of its speed at the end ofeach of its turns, but not when it is also restrained by this spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, the spell freezes ground in the area into difficult terrain for 10 minutes. Frozen ground thaws instantly where there is fire or intense heat.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the cold damage dealt increases by 2d8 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (30 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a glass sphere at least 4 inches in diameter containing any white powder</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Golem Armor" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GOLEM_ARMOR">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a massive hollow construct to armor you, placing yourself in the center of the golem to control it, inside a small cavity that is perfectly sized to fit you and your equipment.</p>
            <p class="indent">Choose one of the following options for your golem armor from the table below, which shows the pages on which you can find the statistics for each option:</p>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr><td>Golem Armo</td><td>Page</td></tr>
                </thead>
                <tr><td>Ice Golem Armor</td><td>154</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Lava Golem Armor</td><td>155</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Metal Golem Armor</td><td>155</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Stone Golem Armor</td><td>156</td></tr>
            </table>
            <p class="indent">The golem armor appears instantly in your space when the spell is cast. You roll initiative for the golem armor, which has its own turns. The golem armor lasts for the duration or until it is reduced to 0 hit points.</p>
            <p class="indent">While you're inside the golem armor, you're paralyzed even if you would normally be immune to the condition, but it doesn't interrupt your concentration on the spell. You see through the golem's eyes and hear through its ears, you completely control the way it moves and the actions it takes, and you have total cover from anything that is outside the golem armor.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the golem armor takes 30 or more damage at once, you must succeed on a Constitution saving throw to maintain concentration on this spell The DC is equal to half of the triggering damage, but you also gain a +5 bonus to the roll</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell fails upon casting if there is not enough unoccupied space around you for the golem armor, or if you are size Huge or larger (since you can't fit inside).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Grand Flood" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GRAND_FLOOD">
        <supports>Cleric, Druid, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You beckon the heavens to flood the land around you. Water rises from the lowest ground point within range. As the water rises and covers more ground, it begins to rise from any ground in the area that is lower than the water leveL covering lower ground before higher ground The water rises 20 feet each round until the spell has conjured an amount of water equal to 20 feet of rainfall averaged across the area, and then stops rising.</p>
            <p clas="indent">While the water rises, it does not spill or flow like normal and stays within the spell's area. Once the water has stopped rising, it flows with gravity and spills onto the terrain outside the area as appropriate.</p>
            <p clas="indent">When the spell ends, the water stops rising and starts to vanish, disappearing over 5 minutes. Living things do not receive nourishment from the water because it will quickly disappear from their bodies.</p>
            <p clas="indent">The spell fails if the caster is indoors or underground when it is cast, and any ground that is indoors or underground is excluded from the spell's area.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">1 mile</set>
            <set name="duration">1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a carved rainstick</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Greater Renewal" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GREATER_RENEWAL">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Druid, Ranger, Inventor, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your magic forces one willing creature that you can see within range to expend great energy as you kindle its body's natural healing processes for an instant. You can cure one poison or disease afflicting the target.</p>
            <p class="indent">The target also gains one level ofexhaustion and regains hit points equal to 25 +your spellcasting modifier (minimum +1) + a number of d6s equal to the target's Constitution modifier (minimum 1d6).</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on constructs, undead, or creatures that are naturally immune to exhaustion.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the healing increases by 2d6 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Great Voice" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GREAT_VOICE">
        <supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your voice booms like rolling thunder. For the duration, when you speak, you can choose to speak up to ten times as loudly as normaL and you can use an action on each ofyour turns to create a wave of sound that roars out from you and can be heard up to 3 miles away.</p>
            <p class="indent">You choose whether the wave is a 60-foot cone emanating from you or a spherical area that extends to30 feet out from you in all directions. Each creatureother than you in the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 4d12 thunder damage, it is pushed 30 feet away from you and knocked prone, and it is deafened for 1 minute. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes half as much damage and nothing else.</p>
            <p class="indent">When you create a wave of sound with this spell unsecured objects that are completely within the area of effect are pushed 30 feet away from you by the spell's effect. You can't create a wave ofsound with this spell if you cannot speak.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">duration</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Guard" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_GUARD">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You shroud yourself or a creature that you touch in a magical ward that has 1d6 hit points and lasts until the end ofyour next turn. Ifthe target would take damage before the spell ends, the ward blocks that damage and takes the damage instead The ward can't block psychic or poison damage unless it is dealt by an attack. If the ward is reduced to O hit points, the target takes any remaining damage and the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">If you target yourself with this spelL it doesn't require concentration.</p>
            <p class="indent">The ward's hit points increase by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), llth level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Halo of Glory" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HALO_OF_GLORY">
        <supports>Cleric, Paladin</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A glowing halo of light appears above the head of a creature you touch and lasts for the duration. The halo sheds bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet, follows the target as it moves, and bathes the target in an impression of heavenly glory, granting it advantage on Charisma (Intimidation) and Charisma (Persuasion) checks.</p>
            <p class="indent">If a creature hits the target with an attack before the spell ends, the halo shoots a ray of light at the attacker, which must make a Dexterity saving throw if it is within 60 feet of the target. On a failed saving throw, the attacker takes 2d6 radiant damage. The spell ends after shooting one ray.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the number of rays the halo can shoot before the spell ends increases by one for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Healing Wave" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HEALING_WAVE">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Druid, Ranger, Paladin, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Healing magic washes out from you and over nearby allies in a rolling wave that amplifies vital energy. You and up to five other creatures ofyour choice within range regain a number of hit points equal to 1d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier,</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifyou are still conscious at the start of your next turn, you and up to five other creatures ofyour choice within range regain hit points again in the same way.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on undead, constructs, or creatures that have 0 hit points.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the healing done at the start ofyour next turn increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 3rd</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">15 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Heat Wave" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HEAT_WAVE">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A wave of nauseatingly hot air swirls briefly in a 50-foot cube emanating from you that spreads around comers. Each creature in the area other than you must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 4d10 fire damage, is poisoned until the end ofyour next tum, and gains one level of exhaustion. On a success, a creature takes half as much damage, is not poisoned, and doesn't gain any exhaustion.</p>
            <p class="indent">A creature has disadvantage on the saving throw if it has resistance or immunity to cold damage. If it has resistance to fire damage or immunity to fire damage, it has advantage on the saving throw and it can't gain any exhaustion from the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">Any levels of exhaustion caused by this spell are removed from a creature when it finishes a short or long rest in a cool or cold environment.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (50 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a chunk of iron</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Heavenly Pillar" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HEAVENLY_PILLAR">
        <supports>Cleric, Paladin, Sorcerer</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You bellow a determined prayer that calls down a pillar of light from the heavens to crush a creature that you can see within range. The target must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, the target takes 5d8 radiant damage and is stunned until the end of your next tum. On a successful saving throw, the target takes half damage and is not stunned</p>
            <p class="indent">If the target is outside and underneath the sky, the spell's damage increases by 2d8.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the damage increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Holy Glare" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HOLY_GLARE">
        <supports>Cleric, Paladin</supports>
        <description>
            <p>With a word, you begin to glow with a circular aura of swirling light that sears and rebukes your foes. For the duration, you shed bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. When a creature ends its tum within 10 feet of you, you can force it to make a Constitution saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a failed saving throw, it takes 3d6 radiant damage and it has disadvantage on any attack rolls made against you before the end of its next turn. On a success, a creature takes half damage and suffers no other effects.</p>
            <p class="indent">Creatures of your choice within 10 feet ofyou have disadvantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight and on saving throws to maintain concentration.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (10 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Howling Void" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HOWLING_VOID">
        <supports>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You destroy the air in a 30-foot radius sphere centered on a point you can see within range, creating an unseen magical area ofvacuum that spreads around corners and lasts until the spell ends. No sound can be created within or pass through the area, and nonmagical flight in the area is impossible. The area disperses gas or vapor, and it extinguishes nonmagical fires of any size. Any creature or object entirely inside the area is immune to thunder damage, is deafened, and cannot breathe or speak.</p>
            <p class="indent">Any creature inside the area when it first appears or that ends its turn within the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 3d8 thunder damage and 3d8 psychic damage and gains one level of exhaustion. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes half damage and does not gain any levels of exhaustion.</p>
            <p class="indent">The damage dealt by this spell ignores resistance and immunity to thunder damage, but not resistance or immunity to all damage. Creatures that are immune to exhaustion are also immune to the psychic damage dealt by this spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">When a creature ends its turn outside the area, it reduces any exhaustion caused by this spell by one level</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bit of earwax</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Hunter's Arrow" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_HUNTERS_ARROW">
        <supports>Ranger</supports>
        <description>
            <p>As part of the action used to cast this spell, you must make a ranged attack with a weapon against one creature within the spell's range, otherwise the spell fails .A spirit of predator beasts guides your strike. You have advantage on the attack roll and for this attack, your weapon counts as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity. On a hit, the target suffers the attack's normal effects and the attack deals 4d8 bonus poison damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">Then, hit or miss, your attack conjures a fey hunting spirit taking the form of a beast and appearing in a space adjacent to the target. The beast is challenge rating 2 or lower, and as a spirit, it gains extra traits in addition to its normal statistics.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Its Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores are each raised to 10 if that score is normally lower than 10. This doesn't confer any additional languages.</li>
                <li>It has resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage dealt by nonmagical weapons.</li>
                <li>It has advantage on attacks made against the target.</li>
                <li>It can move through other creature's spaces and end its turn there.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">The beast is also considered fey, and it disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">The beast is friendly to you and your companions. Roll initiative for the beast - it has its own turns. If the target is still alive, the beast ignores your commands; it will decide how to take its own turns with no goal other than the death of the target. Once the target dies, the beast obeys any verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don't issue any commands, it defends itself from hostile creatures, but otherwise takes no actions if the target is dead.</p>
            <p class="indent">The DM has the beast's statistics.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a ranged weapon</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ice Sculpture" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ICE_SCULPTURE">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a magical chunk of ice into an unoccupied space that you can see within range. The ice created must be no larger than a 10-foot cube, and the ice must be of a form that you have seen before, though the form need not have been made of ice when you saw it. This spell cannot create complicated machinery with moving parts, such as a clock or firearm. When you cast the speli you also choose whether the ice is clear and transparent or cloudy and heavily obscured.</p>
            <p class="indent">The ice has hit points equal to 5d8 + twice your spellcasting modifier (minimum 5 hit points1 and its AC is equal to 10 + your spellcasting modifier. It has immunity to cold damage, but it has vulnerability to bludgeoning, fire, and thunder damage. The ice object is destroyed when it reaches 0 hit points or the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">The ice melts after 2d4 minutes in a hot environment, and only 1 minute in an extremely hot environment.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the hit points of the ice increase by 2d8 for each slot level above 2nd, and the maximum size of the object increases by 5 feet for every 3 slot levels above 2nd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Jolt of Pain" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_JOLT_OF_PAIN">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A bolt ofwhite lightning infused with magical pain leaps from your outstretched finger to strike one creature that you can see within range. You make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 5d8 lightning damage and can't take reactions until the end of your next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent">If damage dealt by this spell forces the target to make a saving throw to maintain concentration, the DC is increased by an amount equal to your spellcasting modifier (minimum +1) and the target has disadvantage on the saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">blue amber worth at least 150 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>
    
    <element name="Leaf Shield" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_LEAF_SHIELD">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch one leaf, petaL or toadstool The object grows and is transformed into a magical shield made out of plant material that lasts for the duration.</p>
            <p class="indent">The magical shield is lightweight and flexible, and it has straps made of stem, root, or vine, so a creature can wield this shield without requiring the use of any hands. When wielded in this way, the shield only increases the wielder's Armor Class by 1.</p>
            <p class="indent">The shield has resistance to all damage and is self-repairing, regaining up to 1 hit point every round When the spell ends, it withers to dust.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> If you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the duration is 1 hour. If you use a spell slot of 5th level or higher, it is 8 hours.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a leaf, petal, or toadstool</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Life Spring" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_LIFE_SPRING">
        <supports>Artificer, Cleric, Ranger, Paladin</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A burst of healing energy blooms into existence in a 15-foot radius sphere centered on a point you can see within range. Up to four creatures ofyour choice within the area each regain hit points equal to 2d6 + your spellcasting ability modifier. Any creature that has more than 0 hit points when it is affected by this spell also gains temporary hit points equal to your spellcasting ability modifier (minimum of one).</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the temporary hit points gained increases by 2 and the healing increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Living Burial" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_LIVING_BURIAL">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>The ground opens beneath one creature on the ground that you can see within range. The target must make a Strength saving throw as magically fluid earth sucks it downward into the ground On a failed saving throw, it takes 7d8 bludgeoning damage and it is pulled 10 feet under the ground and buried until the spell ends (See Appendix A, page 225). On a success, it takes half as much damage and it isn't pulled or buried.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the spell ends, at the end of each of the target's turns while it is still buried, it takes 4d8 nonmagical bludgeoning damage. It can use an action on its turn to attempt to dig upward, making a Strength check against your spellcasting DC. If it succeeds or if the spell ends early, the target makes it up to the surface and is only partially stuck in the ground.</p>
            <p class="indent">While partially stuck, a creature is restrained by the ground itself. It can use an action on its turn to attempt to escape the ground It makes a Strength or Dexterity check (its choice) against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself, falling prone on the ground.</p>
            <p class="indent">If the spell lasts its full duration, the target remains buried permanently, until it escapes or is rescued.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a chunk of bedrock</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Magic Orb" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MAGIC_ORB">
        <supports>Artificer, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure magic into a simple orb of magical air, water, sand, or other inert substance in your hand and use it to strike a creature or object that you can see within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. Ifthe target is within 5 feet of you, you can choose to make a melee spell attack against it instead On a hit, the target takes 1d10 bludgeoning damage. The orb vanishes at the end of the turn.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell's damage increases by 1d10 when you reach 5th level (2d10), 11th level (3d10), and 17th level (4d10).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="March of Blades" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MARCH_OF_BLADES">
        <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a row of synchronized floating blades made of magical energy in a line 30 feet long and 5 feet wide. The line extends in any direction and originates from any point you can see within range. The blades slash in a wide arc as they appear, forcing each creature in the area to make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 3d10 slashing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent">The blades provide half-cover to creatures behind them. You can use a bonus action on subsequent turns to move one or both ends of the line to different locations up to 30 feet away that you can see. When you finish moving the area in this way on a turn, you may choose to have the blades slash again, forcing all creatures in the area to repeat the Dexterity saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent">The blades last until the spell ends, at which point they vanish. If at any time you aren't within range of at least one end of the line, the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the slashing damage dealt increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">any bladed weapon</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Mass Renewal" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MASS_RENEWAL">
        <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You invoke great magic to spark sudden and miraculous healing out of the natural healing capabilities of up to twenty creatures that you can see within range. Each target must be willing or unconscious.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each target gains one level of exhaustion, can cure one poison or disease affecting it, regains hit points equal to 50 + half of its maximum hit points, and must succeecf on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw or gain one additional level of exhaustion. It can also choose to instantly spend hit dice to regain hit points as if it had just finished a short rest, up to a number of hit dice equal to its Constitution modifier (minimum 1 hit die).</p>
            <p class="indent">Any unconscious creature whose maximum hit points are less than 50 automatically fails the Constitution saving throw when healed by this spelL and its body is so drained of energy that it won't regain consciousness until it finishes a long rest.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on creatures that are naturally immune to exhaustion, constructs, or undead</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Mass Shield" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MASS_SHIELD">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Paladin, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A shimmering barrier of magical force appears and protects you and up to two other creatures you can see within range. The attacked creature must be among your targets.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the start ofyour next turn, each affected creature has a +5 bonus to AC, including against the triggering attack, and takes no damage from magic missile. If a creature leaves the range of the spell the effect ends on them.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when you or another creature within range that you can see are hit by an attack or targeted by the magic missile spell</set>
            <set name="range">5 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a woven bracelet</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Megalith" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MEGALITH">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a massive stone orb with a diameter of 20 feet at a point that you can see within range. It crashes into the ground then rolls up to 100 feet in a straight line to an unoccupied space. The orb grants cover and blocks vision. It is an object with 17 AC and 150 hit points, it has vulnerability to thunder damage, and the spell ends if it is destroyed.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each creature in the orb's space when it appears or in its path when it rolls must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 10d12 bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. For the duration, you can use an action on your turn if you are within range of the orb to push it with magic, causing it to roll up to 100 feet in a straight line to an unoccupied space again.</p>
            <p class="indent">The orb deals double damage to objects, but it can't roll through an object unless it deals enough damage to destroy the object. If the orb finishes its movement on an incline, it may roll downhill at the end of that turn (at the DM's discretion), rolling each turn until you use an action to roll it again or it reaches level ground.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the orb vanishes.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">300 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a stone with no moss</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Mighty Roots" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MIGHTY_ROOTS">
        <supports>Druid</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure up to three thick and powerful plant roots, sprouting from the ground in unoccupied spaces you can see within range. The roots are Large and last for the duration, acting like giant tentacles.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each root is an object with AC 16 and 120 hit points that can't be pushed or pulled out of its space. Each root has a Strength of 26 (+8) and a Dexterity of 18 (+4). If a root drops to Ohit points, it is destroyed If all the roots are destroyed, the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">When you cast the spell and as a bonus action on your subsequent turns, you can choose to cause one of the following effects with each of the roots. The roots do not have to perform the same actions as each other. If a creature is in the area of multiple effects, you choose which root it is affected by.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Grab.</em></strong> The root attempts to grapple a Huge or smaller target within 15 feet of it, using its own statistics. If the target is Large or smaller, the root has advantage. At the start of each ofyour turns, you can choose to deal any target grabbed by the roots 5d6 bludgeoning damage.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Slam.</em></strong> The root slams into the ground Each creature in a line 30 feet long and 5 feet wide extending from the root must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 7d8 bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Sweep.</em></strong> The root sweeps along the ground in an arc. Each creature on the ground in a 30-foot cone emitted from the root must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take 6d6 bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Throw.</em></strong> The root hurls whatever it has grabbed up to 60 feet in a direction ofyour choice. The thrown target is knocked prone, and if it strikes a solid surface, it also takes 7d6 bludgeoning damage. If it was thrown toward a creature, that creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take the same bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Misty March" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MISTY_MARCH">
        <supports>Bard, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose up to six creatures that you can see within range. For the duration, each target can use a bonus action on each of its turns while it is within range ofyou to teleport up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space that it can see.</p>
            <p class="indent">Also, on each ofyour turns before the spell ends, you can use an action to teleport each willing target to an unoccupied space that you can see within range. Targets that are more than 500 feet away or on a different plane are not teleported.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Molten Upheaval" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_MOLTEN_UPHEAVAL">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Molten geysers erupt out from the earth in a 40 foot cube centered on a point on the ground that you can see within range. The area extends into the ground and spreads around comers. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw, taking 6d6 fire damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a success.</p>
            <p class="indent">Cracks and fissures filled with molten lava open up in the area and chum the remaining solid earth, making the ground in the area difficult terrain until the spell ends. Any creature that enters the spell's area for the first time on a tum or ends its tum there must make a Dexterity saving throw. A creature takes 6d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much on a success. A creature has disadvantage on the saving throw if it is burrowing or prone, but creatures that aren't touching the ground automatically succeed on the saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell ignites flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried When the spell ends, the ground in the area cools, solidifying into difficult terrain until cleared Each 5-foot-square portion of ground in the area requires at least 10 minutes to clear using mason's tools or a miner's pick.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a chunk of brimstone</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Obliteration Beam" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_OBLITERATION_BEAM">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You emit a massive beam of bright, powerful energy in a line 500 feet long and 25 feet wide that blasts away all in its destructive path. Each creature in the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 11d10 radiant damage and 11d10 force damage, is pushed 50 feet away from you, and is knocked prone. On a success, a creature takes halfas much damage and is not pushed or knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the end ofyour next tum, the area emits bright light for 500 feet and dim light for an additional 500 feet.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell damages and pushes objects in the area.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">500 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a diamond worth at least 800 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ordainment of Colors" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ORDAINMENT_OF_COLORS">
        <supports>Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your body transforms entirely into colorful magical light for the duration, granting you the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You are immune to radiant damage and you have resistance to all damage except psychic damage.</li>
                <li>You ignore the effects of disease, exhaustion, and poisons. Any poisons or diseases already in your system are suspended, not neutralized.</li>
                <li>You cannot be grappled or restrained.</li>
                <li>You can move into and end your turn in the spaces of any objects that light can pass through (such as glass or crystal), but they are difficult terrain for you.</li>
                <li>At the start of each ofyour turns, you choose to glow or stop glowing. While glowing, you shed bright light in a 60-foot radius and dim light for an additional 60 feet, magical darkness is suppressed within 30 feet ofyou, and creatures within 30 feet ofyou can't benefit from invisibility. You choose the light's color.</li>
                <li>When a spell you cast deals radiant damage, it ignores resistance to radiant damage, and it deals extra radiant damage equal to 10 + twice the spell's level A spell can't deal this extra damage to any creature more than once per turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">an opal worth at least 500 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ordainment of Crystal" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ORDAINMENT_OF_CRYSTAL">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your body transforms entirely into magical crystal for the duration. Choose either force or radiant damage. You gain the following benefits while transformed:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You have resistance to all damage.</li>
                <li>You ignore the effects of disease, exhaustion, and poisons. Any poisons or diseases already in your system are suspended, not neutralized.</li>
                <li>When you cast a spell of 1st-level or higher, you can choose one or two creatures that you can see within 60 feet of you. If you chose only one creature, that target takes damage of the chosen type equal to 2d6 + twice the spell's level. Otherwise, each target takes damage equal to 1d6 + the spell's level Treat this damage as if it had come from the magic missile spell (for example, it is blocked by the shield spell), but it ignores resistance to the chosen damage type.</li>
                <li>When another spell you cast deals damage of the chosen type, it ignores resistance to that type, and it deals extra damage of that type equal to 10 + twice the spell's level. A spell can't deal this extra damage to any creature more than once per turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a diamond worth at least 500 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ordainment of Lava" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ORDAINMENT_OF_LAVA">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your body transforms entirely into magical lava for the duration, granting you the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You are immune to fire damage and you have resistance to all damage except cold damage.</li>
                <li>You ignore the effects of disease, exhaustion, and poisons. Any poisons or diseases already in your system are suspended, not neutralized.</li>
                <li>When a creature ends its turn while grappling you or being grappled by you, it takes 8d8 fire damage.</li>
                <li>You can use an action to try to grapple a creature with a free hand made of magic lava. Make a melee spell attack against one creature. On a hit, the target takes 8d8 fire damage and it is grappled by you and restrained while it is grappled The grapple's escape DC is equal to your spell save DC.</li>
                <li>When another spell you cast deals fire damage, it ignores resistance to fire damage, and it deals extra fire damage equal to 10 + twice the spell's level. A spell can't deal this extra damage to any creature more than once per turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a ruby, jacinth, or fire opal worth at least 500 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ordainment of Metal" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ORDAINMENT_OF_METAL">
        <supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your body transforms entirely into magical resonant metal for the duration. Choose one damage type out of bludgeoning, piercing, slashing, or thunder. You gain the following benefits while transformed:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You are immune to thunder damage and you have resistance to all damage except lightning damage.</li>
                <li>You ignore the effects of disease, exhaustion, and poisons. Any poisons or diseases already in your system are suspended, not neutralized.</li>
                <li>You gain a +2 bonus to AC, and your AC can't be less than 18, regardless of what armor you are wearing.</li>
                <li>You are five times as loud, and any creature that sees you can hear you as if you were only 10 feet away.</li>
                <li>You are immune to the silence and howling void spells, and to the effects of being in an environment with high or low pressure. You cannot be prevented from speaking or providing verbal components.</li>
                <li>When a spell you cast deals damage of the chosen type, it ignores resistance to that damage type, and it deals extra damage of that type equal to 10 + twice the spell's level A spell can't deal this extra damage to any creature more than once per turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a small piece of adamantine worth at least 500 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ordainment of Mist" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ORDAINMENT_OF_MIST">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your body transforms entirely into magical icy mist for the duration, granting you the following benefits:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You are immune to cold damage and you have resistance to all damage except fire damage.</li>
                <li>You ignore the effects of disease, exhaustion, and poisons. Any poisons or diseases already in your system are suspended, not neutralized.</li>
                <li>You cannot be grappled or restrained.</li>
                <li>You can use a bonus action on each ofyour turns to release a breath of icy mist in a 30-foot cone which spreads around comers and extinguishes nonmagical flames, lasting until the start ofyour next turn. The area is heavily obscured and difficult terrain. Each creature standing on ground in the area when it appears, that moves or is moved onto ground in the area, or that ends its tum there must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or fall prone.</li>
                <li>When another spell you cast deals cold damage, it ignores resistance to cold damage, and it deals extra cold damage equal to 10+ twice the spell's level A spell can't deal this extra damage to any creature more than once per turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a sapphire or aquamarine worth at least 500 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Ordainment of Storms" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ORDAINMENT_OF_STORMS">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your body transforms entirely into magical clouds for the duration. Choose either lightning or thunder damage. You gain the following benefits while transformed:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You are immune to lightning damage and you have resistance to all damage except thunder damage.</li>
                <li>You ignore the effects of disease, exhaustion, and poisons. Any poisons or diseases already in your system are suspended, not neutralized.</li>
                <li>You cannot be grappled or restrained.</li>
                <li>You have a flying speed of 60 feet, and you can hover. When the spell ends, you fall if you are still aloft, unless you can stop the fall.</li>
                <li>When a spell you cast deals damage of the chosen type, it ignores resistance to that damage type, and it deals extra damage of that type equal to 10+ twice the spell's level A spell can't deal this extra damage to any creature more than once per turn.</li>
            </ul>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">an amber or topaz worth at least 500 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Petrify" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_PETRIFY">
        <supports>Druid, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A beam of amber earthen energy lances from your finger toward one creature that you can see within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, it takes 5d10 necrotic damage, and it must make a Constitution saving throw if it has any limbs. On a failed saving throw, you choose one of its limbs to affect. That limb is turned to stone until the spell ends, and cannot be used to make attacks. The effect of losing a limb can be found in the following table, based on the chosen limb:</p>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr><td>Affected Limb</td><td>Effects of Petrification</td></tr>
                </thead>
                <tr><td>Arm</td><td>The target can no longer hold anything with the affected arm. If it only has one functional arm remaining, it can't hold anything with two hands, and it can hold only a single object at a time. If no arms remain, it can't hold anything at all.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Leg</td><td>The target's speed on foot is halved. If half or more of its legs are not functional and not replaced by prostheses, it must use a cane or crutch to move, it falls prone after using the Dash action, and it has disadvantage on Dexterity checks made to balance. If no legs remain, it can't walk at all, and must crawl.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Wing</td><td>The target's flying speed is halved. If half or more of its wings aren't functional or replaced by prostheses, it cannot fly without the aid of magic.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Tail</td><td>The target's swimming and climbing speeds are halved, except those granted by magic, unless the limb is replaced by a prosthesis.</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Fin</td><td>The target's swimming speed is halved unless it is granted by magic or the limb is replaced by a prosthesis.</td></tr>
            </table>
            <p class="indent">For the duration, the target must make another Constitution saving throw at the end ofeach of its turns. If it successfully saves against this spell two times, the spell ends. If it fails saves four times, it stops making saving throws for this spell The successes and failures don't need to be consecutive; keep track of both until the target collects enough of either kind</p>
            <p class="indent">If you maintain your concentration on this spell for the entire possible duration, the limb stays petrified until the effect is dispelled or removed Any effect that can end the petrified condition or restore a missing limb can also end this effect. Ifthe affected limb is physically broken while petrified, it suffers from similar deformities if it reverts to its original state.</p>
            <p class="indent">Undead, constructs, and creatures that cannot be petrified are entirely immune to this spell.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">petrified bone or amber worth at least 75 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Plasma Coil" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_PLASMA_COIL">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You evoke a whip-like cord ofwrithing plasma in your free hand The whip sheds bright light in a 10-foot radius and dim light for an additional 10 feet and lasts for the duration. Ifyou let go of the whip, it disappears, but you can evoke the whip again as a bonus action.</p>
            <p class="indent">You can use your action to lash out with the whip, which stretches and weaves between foes. Up to five targets ofyour choice that you can see within range must make a Dexterity saving throw. A target takes 5d8 lightning damage and 5d8 force damage on a failed save, or half as much on a success. Objects automatically fail the saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent">Damage from this spell ignores resistance, and it ignores immunity to lightning damage when dealing damage to objects.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Primordial Tides" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_PRIMORDIAL_TIDES">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You release a blast of chaotic magic that washes out from you in a 60-foot cone. Until the spell ends, ground in the area is difficult terrain, and at the end of each of your turns a wave of elemental energy pulses through the area, targeting each creature in the area with a magical effect. The effect is different each round:</p>
            <ul>
                <li><strong>Round 1. </strong>Targets must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, a target takes 7d6 cold damage and its speed is reduced by 20 feet until the next pulse. On a success, a target takes half damage and its speed is not reduced.</li>
                <li><strong>Round 2. </strong>Targets must make a Strength saving throw. On a failure, a target takes 4d6 lightning damage and 3d6 thunder damage and is knocked prone. On a success, a target takes half damage and isn't knocked prone.</li>
                <li><strong>Round 3. </strong>Targets must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failure, a target takes 7d6 fire damage and is lit ablaze. Until a creature takes an action to douse the fire, the target takes 1d10 fire damage at the start of each of its turns. On a success, a target takes half damage and is not lit ablaze.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the fire, cold, and lightning damage dealt all increase by 1d6 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (60-foot cone)</set>
            <set name="duration">3 rounds</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Pyrokinesis" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_PYROKINESIS">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>With a thought, you cause one creature that you can see within range to spontaneously combust. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, the target ignites in flames, taking 1d10 fire damage and burning for the duration.</p>
            <p class="indent">At the start ofeach of its turns while it is burning, the target must repeat the Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it takes 1d6 fire damage. On a successful save, the spell ends. If the target or a creature within 5 feet of it uses an action to put out the flames, or if some other effect douses the flames (such as the target being submerged in water), the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">You can choose to target an object that you can see within range which isn't being worn or carried instead of targeting a creature. Ifyou do, the object automatically fails its saving throws, and it doesn't stop burning when the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the initial damage dealt increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">brimstone or a flame</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Quake Walk" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_QUAKE_WALK">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You begin stomping and grinding your feet, causing the ground around you to temporarily deform like rubber under your earthen magic. Each other creature within 15 feet ofyou must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature is knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the spell ends, the ground within 15 feet of you is difficult terrain for other creatures. In addition, you can use a bonus action on each ofyour turns after the first to stomp the ground, forcing all other creatures within the area to repeat the saving throw, falling prone on a failed save.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell can't affect creatures that aren't on the ground, and only functions while you are on the ground or in the ground and you aren't incapacitated.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (15 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Radic's Sudden Spark" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RADICS_SUDDEN_SPARK">
        <supports>Artificer, Ranger, SOrcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You electrify the attacker's weapon as it strikes its target. The spell deals a creature 2d6 lightning damage on a failed Constitution saving throw, or half as much damage on a successful save. If the attack was a critical hit, the damage increases by 1d6. The spell's target is determined by who made the triggering attack:</p>
             <ul>
                <li><strong>Defensive. </strong>If you were hit by the triggering attack, the attacker rolls the saving throw, with disadvantage if it used a metal weapon to make the attack. On a failed saving throw, it also drops the weapon used in the attack.</li>
                <li><strong>Offensive. </strong>If you made the triggering attack, the target ofyour attack rolls the saving throw, with disadvantage if it is wearing armor made of metal On a failed saving throw, it also can't take reactions until the start ofyour next turn.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when you hit with a melee weapon attack or are hit by a melee weapon attack</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Rainbow" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RAINBOW">
        <supports>Ranger</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a shortbow or longbow (your choice) made of multicolored light into one ofyour hands, which sheds bright light in a 5-foot radius and dim light for an additional 5 feet and lasts for the duration. The weapon is a solid object that you can use to make attacks as normal It is magicai and instead of one bowstring it has seven different bowstrings made of light, with each made of a different color. When you pull one back, a magical arrow made of light of the same color appears upon the bowstring, ready to fire. The arrow disappears when it hits a target. Thus, this weapon doesn't require ammunition to make attacks.</p>
            <p class="indent">When you make a ranged weapon attack using this weapon, you choose one of the following bowstrings. Your attack deals damage of a different type based on that color instead of its normal damage type, it gains the benefits described for that color, and it deals an extra 2d6 damage on a hit.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Red.</em></strong> The attack deals fire damage. On a critical hit, the target is lit ablaze if it is flammable or it is a creature. until a creature takes an action to douse the fire, the target takes 1d10 fire damage at the start of each of its turns.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Orange.</em></strong> The attack deals acid damage. On a critical hit, if the target does not have resistance or immunity to acid damage, it grants attackers advantage on attacks made against it and it doesn't benefit from any damage resistances until the end ofyour next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Yellow.</em></strong> The attack deals lightning damage. On a critical hit, the target is unable to take reactions and has its speed reduced to 0 until the end of its next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Green.</em></strong> The attack deals poison damage. On a critical hit, the target is poisoned until the end ofyour next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Blue.</em></strong> The attack deals cold damage. On a critical hit, the target is restrained until the start of its next turn, and its speed is reduced by 10 feet for 1 minute if it doesn't have resistance or immunity to cold damage.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Indigo.</em></strong> The attack deals necrotic damage. On a critical hit, the target gains one level of exhaustion. This attack has no effect on targets that can't be petrified.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Violet.</em></strong> The attack deals force damage. On a critical hit, you teleport the target up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space that you can see. This attack has no effect on targets that can't be paralyzed.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, while you are wielding this weapon, you can use an action to pull back and release all seven bowstrings at once, ending the spell and releasing a wave of multicolored light and harmonic sound in a line 60 feet long and 15 feet wide. Each creature in the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 6d6 radiant damage and it is blinded and deafened until the end ofyour next turn. On a success, a creature takes half damage and isn't blinded or deafened.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Razor Leaf" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RAZOR_LEAF">
        <supports>Druid</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You hurl a leaf or blade of grass that you are holding at a creature or object within range as your magic aids its flight. Ifyou are not holding a leaf or blade of grass, one is magically plucked from a random non-creature plant within 60 feet ofyou and flies to the target. If there are no leaves or blades of grass within 60 feet of you, the spell fails.</p>
            <p class="indent">Make a spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 1d6 damage. The damage type is determined by the projectile. If you used a needle (such as from a pine tree), the spell deals piercing damage. Otherwise it deals slashing damage. Ifyou were not holding the projectile, the attack determines cover and line of effect as if it was made from the projectile's original location instead ofyour location.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Rejuvenate" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_REJUVENATE">
        <supports>Artificer, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Occultist, Inventor, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You imbue one creature that you touch as part of casting the spell with a magic that revitalizes and protects. Until the spell ends, at the start ofeach of the target's turns, it regains 1d8 hit points and gains a number of temporary hit points equal to 3d6 + twice your spellcasting ability modifier.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a seed or a bit of water</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Relocate" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RELOCATE">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Your magic relocates one other creature that you touch. If the target is willing, it is teleported up to 90 feet to an unoccupied space that you can see.</p>
            <p class="indent">If the target is not willing, you must make a melee spell attack against the target as you attempt to touch it. On a hit, the target must make a Charisma saving throw. On a failed saving throw, the target is teleported up to 90 feet to an unoccupied space that you can see.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Renewal" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RENEWAL">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Druid, Inventor, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You gently apply vital magic to one creature that you touch, causing its body to accelerate its natural healing. The target can expend hit dice and regains hit points as if it had done so during a short rest. The minimum number of hit points the target regains from each hit die expended this way equals your Spellcasting modifier.</p>
            <p class="indent">A creature can only expend up to a number of hit dice equal to its Constitution modifier (minimum of 1) via this spell before it finishes a long rest, no matter how many times the spell is cast or who casts it.</p>
            <p class="indent">At 5th leveL the limit on hit dice expended per long rest is increased by one hit dice. At 11th level it is increased by one more hit dice, and at 17th level it is again increased by one.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">clean water and dressing</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Rescue the Dying" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RESCUE_THE_DYING">
        <supports>Cleric, Druid, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>With a word, you call positive energy into the target's body to heal and ward it. The target regains a number of hit points equal to 4d10 + 30. It also gains temporary hit points equal to half that amount and resistance to all damage, both lasting until the end ofyour next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the healing increases by 2d10 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when another creature within range is reduced to 0 hit points or rolls a death saving throw.</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Resonance" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_RESONANCE">
        <supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You cause nauseating sonic vibrations to pulse from a point ofyour choice within range. The sound fills a 60-foot radius sphere centered on that point for the duration. The area extends beyond total cover, and creatures within the area are deafened At the end of each of your turns until the spell ends, each creature in the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 8d8 thunder damage and it is poisoned for 1 minute. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes halfas much damage and isn't poisoned.</p>
            <p class="indent">While it is poisoned by this spelL a creature's speed is reduced by half and it is deafened Each time it ends its turn outside the area, it must make a Constitution saving throw. On a success, it is no longer poisoned.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell damages objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried if they are made of inorganic material such as stone, crystaL or metal It also deals maximum damage to creatures and objects made ofsuch material.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">300 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a tuning fork</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Sanctify Water" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SANCTIFY_WATER">
        <supports>Cleric, Paladin</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You invoke a holy or unholy blessing upon a 30-foot cube area within range. Until the spell ends, all water within the area is sanctified Choose up to two of the following types of creatures: celestials, elementals, fey, fiends, or undead.</p>
            <p class="indent">When a creature of one of the chosen types starts its turn within the sanctified water or enters it for the first time on a turn, it must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, it takes 3d6 radiant damage and has disadvantage on any attack rolls it makes before the start of its next turn. On a success, it takes half damage and suffers no other effects.</p>
            <p class="indent">When sanctified water is transformed into Holy Water, the ritual to do so only takes 1 minute.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th or 5th leveL the duration increases to 8 hours. When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th or 7th leveL the duration increases to 24 hours. When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the duration increases to 7 days, and ifyou cast thespell with this duration on the same spot once every 7 days for a year, the spell becomes permanent.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">salt, herbs, and incense worth at least 10 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Sand Cloak" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SAND_CLOAK">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You create a swirling cloak ofsand and dust extending 15 feet out from you that lasts for the duration. The area is lightly obscured difficult terrain for other creatures, and it moves with you as you move. You can use a bonus action to reduce or increase the radius of the area, up to a maximum of 15 feet.</p>
            <p class="indent">When a creature other than you enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it is buffeted by sand and dust, and it must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or be blinded until the start of its next turn.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (15 feet)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Sandstorm" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SANDSTORM">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You call a swirling column of sand down to fill a 150-foot-radius, 100-foot-high cylinder that spreads around comers centered on a point you can see within range. For the duration, the area is difficult terrain and heavily obscured Creatures in the area are deafened, and any ranged weapon attacks that pass in or out of the area are made with disadvantage. The sand disperses any vapor, gas, and fog that can be dispersed by strong wind, and it extinguishes unprotected flames if they're Large-sized or smaller.</p>
            <p class="indent">Ifyou're within range of the cylinder, you can move it up to 60 feet as a bonus action on your turn.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> If you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th levei the range is 1 mile. If you use a spell slot of 9th levei the range is Sight.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">500 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bit of sand and a mummified scorpion tail</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Screen of Protection" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SCREEN_OF_PROTECTION">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Paladin, Sorcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You create a magical wall of solid silvery force centered on a point that you can see within range. The wall lasts for the duration. It can be up to 20 feet wide and 20 feet tan but it has no depth. The outward side faces directly away from you, and the inward side faces directly toward you. The wall passes harmlessly through objects when it is created, but after that it blocks the movement of any object that it is not passing through. If the wall passes through any creatures when it is created, the spell fails and the wall vanishes.</p>
            <p class="indent">The wall provides total cover and acts like any solid wall, but it doesn't block sight or any other senses, and anything on the other side is lightly obscured by the wall's colors. Moving through the wall is only possible from the inward side to the outward side, and it costs 15 extra feet ofmovement to pass through. Ranged attacks can pass through the wall with disadvantage if made from the inward side, but are blocked if made from the outward side. Melee attacks are blocked from either side.</p>
            <p class="indent">The wall has 30 hit points and AC equal to 11 + your spellcasting modifier (minimum 12 AC). It automatically fails saving throws for spells and effects. If the wall blocks a spell or effect that deals damage, it takes the damage. If it blocks an attack, the attack is made against it instead, and it takes the damage on a hit.</p>
            <p class="indent">If the wall is reduced to 0 hit points, the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the wall's hit points increase by 15 and its height and width increase by 5 feet for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a mirror or diamond</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Seismic Jaws" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SEISMIC_JAWS">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You chum the earth, causing massive slabs of stone to crash out of the ground and slam together in a 20-foot cube centered on a point on the ground that you can see within range. The area extends into the ground Each creature in the area must make a Constitution saving throw. Flying creatures and Gargantuan creatures have advantage on the saving throw, and burrowing creatures have disadvantage on it.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 5d10 non-magical bludgeoning damage, is stunned until the start ofyour next tum, and is knocked prone. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes half as much damage and suffers no other effects.</p>
            <p class="indent">Additionally, ground within the area becomes difficult terrain until cleared Each 5-foot-square portion of the area requires at least 1 minute to clear by hand.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d10 for each slot level above 6th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a petrified jawbone</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Shelter from Energy" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SHELTER_FROM_ENERGY">
        <supports>Cleric, Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, necrotic, radiant, or thunder, and choose up to six willing creatures you can see within range. For the duration, targets have resistance to that damage type.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, you may target up to one additional willing creature for each slot level above 6th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Shield Other" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SHIELD_OTHER">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Paladin, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A shimmering barrier of magical force appears and protects the attacked creature. Until the start ofyour next turn, the target has a +5 bonus to AC, including against the triggering attack, and it takes no damage from magic missile.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take when another creature within range that you can see is hit by an attack or targeted by the magic missile spell</set>
            <set name="range">15 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a bead bracelet</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Shining Armor" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SHINING_ARMOR">
        <supports>Cleric, Paladin, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You wreathe yourself in weightless magical armoring crafted from plates of pure light. Until the spell ends, you shed bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an extra 20 feet. You also gain the following benefits for the duration:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>When a creature within 10 feet ofyou hits you with a melee attack, the plates burst with beams of light. The attacker takes 3d6 radiant damage, and other creatures ofyour choice within 10 feet ofyou take half that damage.</li>
                <li>Attacks made against you have disadvantage.</li>
                <li>You have resistance to radiant damage.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">In addition, if you are critically hit before the spell ends, you can use your reaction to end the spelL causing the plates to explode in a protective blast of light. The attack misses, and the attacker as well as each creature ofyour choice within 10 feet ofyou must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become blinded until the end ofyour next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the magical plates vanish.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a glass orb</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Sinking Maw" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SINKING_MAW">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose a point on the ground that you can see within range. Ground within 30 feet of that point becomes swirling sand until the spell ends. The sand is difficult terrain. Each creature standing on the sand when the spell is cast must make a Dexterity saving throw. Any creature that enters the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn within the area must also make the saving throw. On a failure, a creature sinks halfway into the sand and becomes restrained by the ground</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the spell ends, if a creature ends its turn while restrained by the ground in this way, it is pulled up to 10 feet toward the center of the area.A restrained creature can use its action to make a Strength or Dexterity check (its choice) against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself and clambers onto the surface.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, either because your concentration is broken or because you decide to end it, the ground returns to the solid form it had before the spell was cast. Each creature restrained by the spell must make a Constitution saving throw. A creature takes 9d6 nonmagical bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success. Creatures are still restrained by the solid ground (not by any creature or spell) until they escape, and they have disadvantage on ability checks made to escape solid ground.</p>
            <p class="indent">Creatures with a burrowing speed can't be restrained by the ground using this spell.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">an antlion shell filled with sand</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Soar" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SOAR">
        <supports>Artificer, Ranger, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a willing creature. The target gains a flying speed of 120 feet for the duration. While the target is flying using this speed, it gains a +1 bonus to AC, it has advantage on Dexterity saving throws, and opportunity attacks it provokes by flying have disadvantage. When the spell ends, the target falls if it is still aloft, unless it can stop the fall.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, you can target one additional creature in range for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">an arrow or dart</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Sonic Boom" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SONIC_BOOM">
        <supports>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>A bead of thunderous force rockets from your fingertips toward a point you can see within range, where it explodes into a wave ofsound that expands to a 20-foot radius sphere centered on that point. Each creature within the area must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 5d10 thunder damage, is deafened until the end ofyour next turn, is knocked prone, and is pushed 20 feet away from the center of the area. On a successful save, a creature takes half damage and is not knocked prone, pushed, or deafened.</p>
            <p class="indent">Unsecured objects that are completely within the area of effect are automatically pushed 20 feet away from the center of the area by the spell's effect.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d10 and the distance a creature is pushed increases by 5 feet for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Stampede of Savagery" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STAMPEDE_OF_SAVAGERY">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You call fey spirits to appear as wave of frenzied beasts, which washes over your enemies like a storm of fang and claw in your choice of either a 60-foot-tall cylinder with a 20-foot radius centered on a point you can see within range, or as a 60-foot cone emanating from you. Ten fey spirits taking the form of beasts appear in unoccupied spaces of your choice within the area. Each beast is challenge rating 1/4 or lower and is also considered fey. A beast disappears when it drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the beasts appear, each other creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw, taking 2d8 piercing damage, 2d8 bludgeoning damage, and 2d8 slashing damage on a failure, or half as much damage on a success. This damage is nonmagical.</p>
            <p class="indent">The summoned beasts are friendly to you and your companions. Roll initiative for the beasts as a group, which has its own turns. They obey any verbal commands that you issue to them (no action required by you). If you don't issue any commands to them, they defend themselves from hostile creatures, but otherwise take no actions.</p>
            <p class="indent">The DM has the creatures' statistics.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the bludgeoning damage increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 5th. In addition, when you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, twice as many creatures appear.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of animal dung</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Starlight" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STARLIGHT">
        <supports>Warlock</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You call eerie starlight down upon one creature you can see within range. The target's space is filled with dim light until the end ofyour next turn, and it must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, it becomes charmed for the duration. While charmed by the spell a creature is incapacitated and it can't move or speak.</p>
            <p class="indent">The target repeats the Wisdom saving throw at the end ofeach of its turns, ending the spell on a success. The spell also ends if the target takes any damage or if someone else uses an action to touch the target and shake it out of its stupor. The target has disadvantage on the first saving throw if it can see the sky and it is night. If the target is blinded or can't see, it automatically succeeds on any saving throw for the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the target doesn't repeat the saving throw on its turns. Ifyou use a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the duration is concentration, up to 10 minutes.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a star chart or astrolabe</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Star Step" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STAR_STEP">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You step through the realm of stars, teleporting yourself to an unoccupied space you can see within range. Immediately after you appear, a blast of light and magical energy courses out of the portal you stepped through. Each other creature within 30 feet ofyou must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 3d8 force damage and 3d8 radiant damage, it is knocked prone, and it is blinded until the start of your next turn. On a success, a creature takes half damage and isn't knocked prone or blinded.</p>
            <p class="indent">You can bring along objects as long as their weight doesn't exceed what you can carry. You can also teleport one willing creature of your size or smaller who is carrying gear up to its carrying capacity. That creature doesn't roll the saving throw. It must be within 5 feet of you when you cast this speli and there must be an unoccupied space within 5 feet ofyour destination space for the creature to appear in; otherwise, the creature is left behind.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the radiant damage done increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 6th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Steam Strike" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STEAM_STRIKE">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You launch a curling blast of scalding hot steam at one creature that you can see within range. Make a ranged spell attack against the target. On a hit, it takes 11d4 fire damage and must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become blinded for 1 minute. It repeats the saving throw at the end ofeach of its turns, ending the blindness on a success. On a miss, the target takes half damage and is not blinded.</p>
            <p class="indent">Hit or miss, the target's space is filled with steam and mist that makes it lightly obscured until the end of your next turn or until a wind of any speed disperses it.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 2d4 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Stockade Sprouts" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SOCKADE_SPROUTS">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You cause up to four trees to magically sprout at locations of your choice that you can see on the ground within range. Each creature that is directly above one of the locations must make a Dexterity saving throw, as the trees suddenly grow to full size and form cages with their branches. On a success, a creature can use its reaction to move up to half its speed to an unoccupied space to escape the branches. If it does not, it is trapped by the branches of the growing tree.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each creature trapped inside the branches is restrained and held at the top of the tree. A trapped creature can use its action to make a Strength or Dexterity check (its choice) against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself.</p>
            <p class="indent">You decide each tree's height. They can be as short as 5 feet and as tall as 20 feet. The trunks of the trees are 3 feet wide. The trees are solid objects that provide cover, and the tops of the trees are lightly obscured by leaves. The insides of the branch cages are lined with poisonous leaves and vines. Once per turn when a trapped creature makes a weapon attack or fails an ability check to escape, it must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 3d6 poison damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the trees vanish, and any creatures trapped inside are freed A freed creature falls if it cannot fly or climb the tree using a climbing speed.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the number of trees you can cause to sprout increases by one for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">90 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">an acorn for each tree sprouted</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Stone Blast" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STONE_BLAST">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You summon a group of large stones from a space next to a surface within range that you can see, like a floor, wan or ceiling. The surface doesn't have to be made of a single contiguous materiai but it must be mostly made of earth, sand, stone, metai crystai or another suitable earthen or stone-like materiai and it must be at least 3 inches deep, or else the spell fails.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the stones appear from the surface, you make two spell attacks, magically hurling the stones at targets you can see within 60 feet of the stones' location. Each attack deals 2d6 nonmagical bludgeoning damage on a hit. You may choose a different target or the same target for any of the attacks, but all targets must be within 30 feet of each other.</p>
            <p class="indent">The spell attacks you make with this spell determine cover and line of effect as if they were made from the location where the stones were summoned instead of your location, and they ignore disadvantage caused by a target being prone.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you make one additional attack with the stones for each slot level above 1st.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Storm God's Haste" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STORM_GODS_HASTE">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You touch a willing creature and invest it with lightning speed Until the spell ends, the target's speed is tripled, it gains a +3 bonus to AC, it has advantage on Dexterity saving throws, and it gains two additional actions on each of its turns. These actions can be used only to take the Attack (one weapon attack only), Dash, Disengage, Hide, or Use an Object action.</p>
            <p class="indent">For the duration, the target also has resistance to lightning damage, has advantage on weapon attack rolls, and deals 1d6 bonus lightning damage when it hits with a weapon attack. In addition, it can use a bonus action on its tum to teleport in a flash of lightning up to 15 feet to an unoccupied space that it can see.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the target falls prone and is both stunned and paralyzed until the end of its next turn, as a wave of lethargy and electricity, and pain sweeps over it. A creature affected by this spell gains no benefit from the haste spell.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a coil of copper</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Storm Spear" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_STORM_SPEAR">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You form lightning into a crackling spear of energy, which you use to either make one melee spell attack against a target within 5 feet ofyou or one ranged spell attack against a target that you can see within range. Then the spear vanishes.</p>
            <p class="indent">On a hit, the target takes 6d8 + 20 lightning damage, and if it isn't immune to the damage, it must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, it falls prone and becomes paralyzed and stunned for the duration. It repeats the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on a success. On a miss, the target takes half as much damage and suffers no other effects from the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 2d8 for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">7</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Summon Primal Spirit" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SUMMON_PRIMAL_SPIRIT">
        <supports>Druid</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You commune with an ancient elemental or fey, the one that most resembles the totem you used for a material component as interpreted via ancient traditions. If you have not already become one of the spirit's champions, this spell only lets you mentally communicate with the spirit for the duration. You perceive this as a meeting with the spirit that occurs in the spirit's home realm. If you can convince it that you are worthy of being one of its champions before the spell ends (DM's discretion), you gain the ability to summon it using that totem as a material component when casting the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">If you are already one of the spirit's champions when you cast the speli you can instead choose to conjure that spirit as a powerful avatar to fight as your ally, taking the form of a creature of challenge rating 12 or lower in an unoccupied space within range. The avatar is also considered fey or elemental (based on which type the spirit is), and it can speak and understand Druidic.</p>
            <p class="indent">The avatar is friendly to you and your companions. Roll initiative for the avatar, which has its own turns. The avatar obeys any verbal commands that you issue to it (no action required by you). If you don't issue any commands to it, it defends itself from hostile creatures, but otherwise takes no actions.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the avatar drops to 0 hit points or when the spell ends, the avatar disappears, and the spirit remains in its home realm. It is unharmed and unperturbed by anything that happened to the avatar during the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">The DM has the avatar creature's statistics.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a totem carved to represent a specific primal spirit worth at least 200 gp</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Sun Flower" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SUN_FLOWER">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a huge spectral sunflower which rises from the ground at a point that you can see within range and lasts for the duration. The flower sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet, which is sunlight. The flower is incorporeal and does not occupy space. You can use a bonus action on each of your turns before the spell ends to cause the flower to release blazing sunlight in a blast. Choose one of the following two options each time you do so.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Area Blast.</em></strong> Choose either a 15-foot-radius, 100-foot-high cylinder centered on the flower, a 40-foot cone blasting from the flower, or a line 80 feet long and 5 feet wide blasting from the flower. Each creature in the chosen area must make a Constitution saving throw, taking 6d6 radiant damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success. Undead and oozes have disadvantage on this roll.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Single Target.</em></strong> Make a ranged spell attack against a target within 150 feet of the flower that you can see. Determine cover and line of effect for this attack as if it was made from the flower's location rather than your location. On a hit, the target takes 8d6 radiant damage. You have advantage on this attack roll against undead and oozes.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 5th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a sunflower seed</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Swelling Storm" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SWELLING_STORM">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You summon a column of soft rain, mist, and electrified air in a 60-foot-tall cylinder with a 30-foot radius centered on a point you choose within range that lasts untilthe spell ends. The area is lightly obscured.</p>
            <p class="indent">Until the spell ends, on each ofyour turns, you can use an action to strengthen the spell with your magic. If you do, the radius of the area grows by 10 feet for the duration. This cannot extend the radius beyond 60 feet.</p>
            <p class="indent">At the end of each ofyour turns while the spell lasts, lightning pulses, and each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 3d8 lightning damage, or 6d8 lightning damage if you cast the spell this turn or you used your action to strengthen it this turn. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes half damage.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the max radius for the area increases by 20 feet for each slot level above 7th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Swift Ward" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SWIFT_WARD">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You ward yourself in a hasty barrier of magical energy to protect against danger, granting you a protective ward that lasts until the end ofyour next turn.</p>
            <p class="indent">The ward has hit points equal to 6d6 + twice your spellcasting ability modifier. Ifyou would take damage, the ward blocks and takes that damage instead. The ward cannot block psychic or poison damage unless it is dealt by an attack. Ifthe ward is reduced to 0 hit points, you take any remaining damage and the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the ward hit points increase by 2d6 for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Abjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take just before you would take damage</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Swoop" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_SWOOP">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You take to the air in a burst of brief magical flight. You have a 60 foot flying speed for this turn only. You fall if you are still aloft when the turn ends, unless you can stop the fall.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 reaction, which you take immediately after the start of your turn</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">1 turn</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a leaf</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Tend Plants" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TEND_PLANTS">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You choose any number of non-creature plants that you can see within range in a 5 foot cube. This spell can affect plants that do not fit entirely within the area, but it only affects the portions of those plants that are inside the area. You manipulate the affected plants in one of the following ways.</p>
            <ul>
                <li>You change the color, taste, or texture of any of the plants' leaves, petals, or fruit. You can use this to create messages. These changes last for 1 hour.</li>
                <li>You cause the plants to shake and twist, releasing any ripe fruits or ready seeds and knocking off any tiny pests such as bugs or mice. For 1 hour, such pests can't consume the plant or climb on it. This only affects Tiny creatures that don't have a level or CR greater than 0.</li>
                <li>You cause the plants or part of the plants to move up to 5 feet in a direction ofyour choice. This can't relocate a plant that is firmly rooted in the ground nor does it change the flexibility of the plants, but it can cause vines to rise and coiL branches to shake, tumbleweeds to rolL etc. This movement doesn't have enough force to cause damage.</li>
                <li>You cause the plants to twist into knots. For 1 hour, the plants are difficult terrain for any creature walking through them, and climbing the plants does not cost any extra movement.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent">If you cast this spell multiple times, you can have no more than two of its non-instantaneous effects active at a time, and you can dismiss such an effect as an action.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous or 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Terra Spike" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TERRA_SPIKE">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose a creature or object that you can see which is adjacent to a surface within range, like a floor, wall or ceiling. The surface doesn't have to be made of a single contiguous materil, but it must be mostly made of earth, sand, stone, metaL crystaL or another suitable earthen or stone-like materiaL and it must be at least 6 inches deep, or else the spell fails.</p>
            <p class="indent">You summon a solid spike out of the surface material to impale the target, which must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, the target takes 3d10 nonmagical piercing damage, or half damage on a success. Ifthe target is flat against the surface, such as a prone target being spiked from the ground, the target is imperiled, giving it disadvantage on the saving throw and increasing the damage dealt from 3d10 to 3dl2. The spike crumbles to dust after the saving throw.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d10 or 1d12 if the target is imperiled for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">2</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a flake of igneous rock</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Terra Steed" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TERRA_STEED">
        <supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure an earthen boulder, which you leap atop as part of casting the spelL and your magic causes it to float and fly. You gain a flying speed of 30 feet for the duration. While you fly in this way, the boulder remains beneath you and can provide half cover. If you fall while flying in this way, the spell ends immediately.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, if you fly at least 20 feet straight toward a target using this flying speed on your turn, you can use your bonus action to slam the target using the boulder. Make a melee spell attack against the target. On a hit, the target takes 2d6 nonmagical bludgeoning damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, the boulder turns to dust and you fall if you are still aloft, unless you can stop the fall.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the flying speed you gain increases by 30 feet for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a pebble or small rock</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Topple" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TOPPLE">
        <supports>Artificer, Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You attempt to knock over one creature that you can see within range using kinetic force. The target must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 1d4 bludgeoning damage and is knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell's damage increases by 1d4 when you reach 5th level (2d4), 11th level (3d4), and 17th level (4d4).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">30 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of dirt</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Torch of Life" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TORCH_OF_LIFE">
        <supports>Cleric, Druid, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You ignite a powerful storm of life energy within the soul ofone creature that you can see within range. While the spell lasts, at the end ofeach ofyour turns while you are within range of the target, you restore hit points to the target equal to half of its maximum hit points and restore 4d8 hit points to up to six other creatures ofyour choice within 30 feet of the target.</p>
            <p class="indent">In addition, until the spell ends, the target does not lose consciousness or become incapacitated for reaching 0 hit points. This does not prevent death.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a flame</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Toxic Breath" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TOXIC_BREATH">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You exhale a cloud of misty vapor in a 30 foot cone in front of you. Each creature in the cone must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failure, a creature takes 8d6 poison damage, and it is poisoned until the start of your next turn. While poisoned in this way, its speed is reduced by half. On a success, a creature takes half damage and is not poisoned.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage dealt increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">3</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (30-foot cone)</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a lead ring or green dragon's scale</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Trailblazer" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_TRAILBLAZER">
        <supports>Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Flames erupt from your back and swirl in a cyclone around your legs to propel you rapidly forward When the spell is cast and at the start ofeach of your turns until the spell ends, you gain 60 extra feet of movement for that turn only. In addition, you gain the following benefits for the duration:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Your jumping distance is tripled.</li>
                <li>You do not provoke opportunity attacks by moving.</li>
                <li>You can move through other creatures' spaces, and you can move along vertical surfaces and across liquids without falling, but only on your turns.</li>
                <li>When you move into a creature's space for the first time on one ofyour turns, that creature must make a Strength saving throw. On a failure , it takes 6d6 fire damage and is knocked prone. On a success, it takes half damage and isn't knocked prone. If you end your turn in an occupied space, you fall prone in the nearest unoccupied space.</li>
                <li>When you move across the ground on your turn, you leave an area of flames in your wake that lasts until the end ofyour next turn. The path of fire is as wide as your space and reaches 5 feet high. When another creature ends its turn within the flames, it takes 4d6 fire damage.</li>
            </ul>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, the damage dealt on your turns increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 6th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a matchstick or a piece of flint</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Wall of Lava" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WALL_OF_LAVA">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You create a wall of lava on a solid surface within range. You can make the wall up to 100 feet long and 30 feet high, or a ringed wall up to 50 feet in diameter and 30 feet high. The wall is 3 feet thick. It is opaque, sheds dim light for 30 feet, and lasts for the duration.</p>
            <p class="indent">When the wall appears, each creature within its area must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 8d8 fire damage and is restrained by the wall On a success, it takes half damage and it is pushed out of the wall's space. Any creature that ends its tum within 5 feet of the wall takes 4d8 fire damage.</p>
            <p class="indent">Creatures can enter and move through the wall, but they must spend 6 feet of movement for every 1 foot moved through it. A creature that enters the wall's space for the first time on a tum or ends its tum there takes 8d8 fire damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be restrained by the wall A restrained creature can use its action to make a Strength check against your spell save DC. On a success, it frees itself.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell ignites flammable objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>Obsidian.</em></strong>  Spells that deal more than 20 cold damage and pass through the wall cause the wall to freeze into solid obsidian glass where the spell passed through it (at least a 5-foot square section is frozen). Each 5-foot- square obsidian section hasAC 12 and 30 hit points and is vulnerable to thunder damage. Reducing an obsidian section to 0 hit points destroys it. When a section is destroyed, the wall's lava doesn't fill it.</p>
            <p class="indent">If you maintain your concentration on this spell for its entire duration, the wall hardens permanently into obsidian glass instead ofvanishing, and it can't be dispelled Without the spell's magic to maintain them, the destruction of the panels might now cause other connected panels to collapse at the DM's discretion.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a small piece of obsidian</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Water Spout" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WATER_SPOUT">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure a stream of pressurized magical water that sprays toward your target. One creature you can see within range must make a Strength saving throw. On a failure, the target takes 1d6 bludgeoning damage and if it is Large or smaller, you push it 10 feet away from you.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell conjures 4 gallons of stale water for each die of damage rolled This water cannot sustain life and instantly vanishes when the spell ends.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell's damage increases by 1d6 when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">1 round</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Water to Acid" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WATER_TO_ACID">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Warlock, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>Choose a point you can see within range inside a body ofwater. The portions of that body of water that fit inside a SO-foot cube centered on that point become highly acidic until the spell ends. Any creature that ends its tum within the area takes 7d4 acid damage and must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature is blinded until the end of its next tum. Objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried also take damage at the end of each ofyour turns.</p>
            <p class="indent">While the spell lasts, your magic keeps the acid in the area from mingling with the surrounding water. When the spell ends, the acid returns to its original form as water. This does not alter the composition of the water.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">5</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">120 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a vial of acid and a lump of coal</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Water Whip" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WATER_WHIP">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You conjure water in the shape of a tentacle-like whip in your free hand The whip flows from your arm and lasts for the duration. Ifyou let go of the whip, it disappears, but you can conjure it again as a bonus action.</p>
            <p class="indent">You can use your action to make a melee spell attack with the whip that has a reach of 10 feet. On a hit, the target takes 3d4 bludgeoning damage, or you can choose to trip the target, dealing it no damage and knocking it prone instead.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the reach of the spell attack increases by 5 feet for each slot level above 1st. When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, you can conjure a second whip in another hand as part of the same bonus action, and with two whips you can make two spell attacks using your action instead of only one.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">1</set>
            <set name="school">Conjuration</set>
            <set name="time">1 bonus action</set>
            <set name="range">Self</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">seaweed or an octopus tentacle</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Weathering" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WEATHERING">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You alter the composition ofone object that you touch, changing it as if much time has passed Choose either three hours or three days. The object instantly changes as if that much time had passed This can cause paint to dry and eventually chip away, cause concrete to harden and eventually crack, erode stone, make paper rot, etc.</p>
            <p class="indent">The rate at which the object changes is determined by its current conditions. For example, paper will rot more quickly in warm climates, and stone will erode faster if placed in the path of moving water.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell can't cause damage to a magic item, and it can't affect any spells or magical effects.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">0</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 minute</set>
            <set name="range">Touch</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a pinch of sand, dust, or mulch</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Windcage" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WINDCAGE">
        <supports>Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You point at a creature you can see within range, and a powerful gust of wind blows in and carries it away. You push the creature up to 60 feet in any direction, including off the ground and into the air. Until the spell ends, the creature is restrained by the swirling wind.</p>
            <p class="indent">While restrained in this way, the target does not fan it takes 4d10 bludgeoning damage at the end of each of its turns, and you can use a bonus action on each ofyour turns after the first to push the target up to 60 feet in any direction, including through the air.</p>
            <p class="indent">The target can use its action to attempt to escape. It makes a Strength or Dexterity check (its choice) against your spell save DC, with advantage if it has a flying speed On a success, it frees itself. Once a creature is no longer restrained by the spelL it falls if it is still aloft, unless it can stop the fall.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">8</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">150 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Wind Funnel" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WIND_FUNNEL">
        <supports>Artificer, Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Inventor</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You unleash a powerful torrent of swirling wind that pulls in a roaring cyclone toward you, creating a 60-foot cone blasting out from you that spreads around corners. Each other creature in the area must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed saving throw, a creature takes 3d8 thunder damage and 3d8 bludgeoning damage, and it is pulled 30 feet closer to you and knocked prone. On a successful saving throw, a creature takes half damage and isn't pulled or knocked prone.</p>
            <p class="indent">Unsecured objects that are completely within the area of effect are automatically pulled 30 feet closer to you by the spell's effect, but a cushion of air that swirls around you stops their movement before they enter your space or damage you.</p>
            <p class="indent"><strong><em>At Higher Levels.</em></strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the bludgeoning damage dealt increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 4th.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">4</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (60-foot cone)</set>
            <set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">an empty bottle with stopper</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">false</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Wind Wake" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_WIND_WAKE">
        <supports>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Occultist</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You point in a direction and wake the four winds to your aid Until the spell ends, a hurricane-force wind blows inside a 200-foot cube centered on you that follows you. The wind blows from one end of the cube to the other in the chosen direction, but it doesn't affect you.</p>
            <p class="indent">The wind disperses gas or vapor and extinguishes all flames within the area. Any ranged weapon attacks that pass into or through the area automatically miss, and creatures have advantage on any saving throws made against breath effects that blow against the direction of the wind At the end of each ofyour turns while the spell lasts, any unsecured objects that are completely within the area of effect are automatically pushed 60 feet away from you by the wind.</p>
            <p class="indent">Other creatures within the area are deafened, and must spend 5 feet of movement for every 1 foot moved against the direction of the wind In addition, other creatures can't fly within the area. Ifone is flying when it enters the area, it falls if it can't hover.</p>
            <p class="indent">Each other creature that enters the area for the first time on a tum or starts its tum in the area must make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, a creature is pushed 60 feet in the direction of the wind, or pushed only 15 feet on a success. A creature can choose to fail this save automatically.</p>
            <p class="indent">As a bonus action on each ofyour turns before the spell ends, you can change the direction of the cube and the wind.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">9</set>
            <set name="school">Transmutation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">Self (200-foot cube)</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
            <set name="materialComponent">a conductor's baton</set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

    <element name="Zone of Restoration" type="Spell" source="The Elements and Beyond" id="ID_TEAB_SPELL_ZONE_OF_RESTORATION">
        <supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid</supports>
        <description>
            <p>You evoke an area of healing magic in the shape of a 25-foot radius sphere centered on a point you choose that you can see within range. The area is filled with sparkling dim light, and it lasts for the duration.</p>
            <p class="indent">Whenever a friendly creature enters the area for the first time on a tum or starts its tum within the area, it regains a number of hit points equal to 2d4 + your spellcasting ability modifier. Ifthe spell has already healed the creature, it gains that many temporary hit points instead</p>
            <p class="indent">When the spell ends, all temporary hit points granted by this spell disappear, but up to ten creatures ofyour choice each regain hit points equal to the temporary hit points that they had remaining from the spell.</p>
            <p class="indent">This spell has no effect on undead or constructs.</p>
        </description>
        <setters>
            <set name="keywords"></set>
            <set name="level">6</set>
            <set name="school">Evocation</set>
            <set name="time">1 action</set>
            <set name="range">60 feet</set>
            <set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
            <set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
            <set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
            <set name="materialComponent"></set>
            <set name="isConcentration">true</set>
            <set name="isRitual">false</set>
        </setters>
    </element>

<p class="indent"></p>
</elements>